<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The blood of the grape republished and enlarged by the author To. Whitaker.</title>
            <author>Whitaker, Tobias, d. 1666.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1654</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 127 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 73 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A65691</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W1714</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R187810</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">10581657</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 10581657</idno>
            <idno type="VID">45272</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A65691)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 45272)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1391:26)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The blood of the grape republished and enlarged by the author To. Whitaker.</title>
                  <author>Whitaker, Tobias, d. 1666.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[12], 132 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>For Samuel Brown,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[S.l.] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1654.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Wine --  Therapeutic use.</term>
               <term>Wine and wine making.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Amanda Flynn</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Amanda Flynn</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:45272:1"/>
            <p>THE BLOOD OF THE GRAPE Republiſhed and enlarged by the Author TO: WHITAKER M: D: Phiſitian in Ordinarie to his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties Houſe-hould</p>
            <p>(Printed) For <hi>SAMVEL BROVN.</hi> MDCLIIII.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_gentle_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:45272:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:45272:2"/>
            <head>Gentle Reader.</head>
            <p>I Am not ignorant, that there be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longeth to Kings from their ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants both Tribute of duty, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſents of affection, elce it wil appeare a tacit denial of any grace or boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty received from them; as for the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer of theſe (I hope) I ſhal not live to be wanting in my moſt humble duty, and the good pleaſure of his Majeſties imployments; and for the latter (I conceave) the choice of this ſubject might be an oblation much referring to the excellency of his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dividual perſon. And were the forme as Courtlie as the matter, I could have had the confidence, to crave the Patronage of the Higheſt borne <hi>Prince</hi> of the Chriſtian world, and a Perſon (without flattery) in whom
<pb facs="tcp:45272:3"/>all greateſt Crownes concentrate, though at preſent as highly beyond all Law of nature, or national exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, injured &amp; traterouſly treated: which offereth the cauſe of this may republication, with a further enlarge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of my former act, in the yeare 1638. as being ſenſible of a vulgar miſunderſtanding of my intention in the tractation of this ſubect, which was then, and is now, but an addition to our medicinal faculty, &amp; more ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actly to declare, how, and after what manner the juce of the Grape may be conducible to humane bodyes, both for Aliment and Medicament: which if thoſe <hi>Lords</hi> and <hi>Commons</hi> that would ſuffer noe perſons of honour and loyalty to make with themſelves the repreſentative body of the whole Kingdome, if thoſe (I ſay) had accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, it in my owne ſenſe, could not in
<pb facs="tcp:45272:3"/>ſuch a Noaical ſtupefaction, have ſlept out their Eyes of reaſon and ſenſe of honour, as to ſuffer their na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kednes to be detected by the moſt common Robbers of the Engliſh Nation, and themſelves impriſoned for the ſame theft. If they ſhal excuſe themſelves, and that ſuch ebriety was not the cauſe, they can not ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare any other then the Tred of Dunghill-Cocks, for no ſpirit of the Game or reaſonable, could ſuffer or conceive, that the ſtoping up the fountaine of honour, could render the rivolets any other then ſtincking Ditches: if otherwiſe ſuch ſtupidity were conveyed in their baſe Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of nature, 'tis then a <hi>Gengrena</hi> in the maſſe of blood, and by noe ot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>her ſcope to be cured, but by extir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pation and replanting more noble and lively Rootes in their roome; If
<pb facs="tcp:45272:4"/>any perſon ſhal adjudge this ſharpe Councel to be more <hi>medicall,</hi> then <hi>prudential,</hi> which terme in this age is the perfect Character of a cheating and treacherous villayne or knave, which formerly obteyned a better ſignification, let them know the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſultor is more <hi>Medical</hi> then <hi>Pruden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial</hi> &amp; well knowing his faculty to be ſufficiently comprehenſive of all arts and ſciences and Politicks, if either <hi>Ariſtotel</hi> or <hi>Machivel</hi> are eſteemed Pollititians, and ſo ſuch as have been endowed with ſuch perfection of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tellect amongſt the Profeſſors of this faculty, the Almighty hath Crowned with a ſpecial title of honour as hath in many ages appeared by the ſtud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dys and practiſe of great Kings, and hath ben the fountaine of the whole famely <hi>de Medicis,</hi> ſoe great at this day: nor are there any (except the ſou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les
<pb facs="tcp:45272:4"/>of <hi>Cornelius Agrippa</hi>) ſoe vaine, as to render an undervallue of the faculty, or beſmeere the Purple and Scarlet Robes of the Phiſitian <hi>Cum ſtircore &amp; Vrinâ;</hi> were my ſelfe over zealous, by its ſubject matter I could demonſtrate it for Antiquity to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cede the Forme, in that matter, which was by the Almighty after informed, and as ſoone as the ſex was diſtingui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed it was <hi>Corpus humanum, vivens &amp; ſanabile,</hi> and inſtantly the ſubject of that part of Phiſick which we call <hi>Diaetetical,</hi> as appeareth by their ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity in eating of all manner of Ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in <hi>Paradiſe</hi> by the order of the <hi>Creator</hi> (except the <hi>Tree of Life</hi>) and not only for antiquity, but alſo for its dignity of frame, about which the Almighty ſummoned a Councel, and left moſt juſtly from its owne excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency, to challenge precedence of all
<pb facs="tcp:45272:5"/>other ſubjects of ſciences and arts (except <hi>Theologie</hi>) which is ſubjected principally in the forme: it is alſo af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed by the Orator in the 2 <hi>de na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tura Deorum,</hi> that al Creatures are dedicated to its ſervice: and <hi>Ioſephus</hi> wil create it Lord of al Terreſtrialitie and the cauſe of al ſuch production according to <hi>Plinie:</hi> As for any larger Encomiaſtick I ſhal referr the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to <hi>Lactantius,</hi> and leave <hi>Corne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius</hi> with his vanitles, to the <hi>pruden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tials</hi> of theſe times, which would have all knowledge &amp; virtue to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt in ſelfe confidence &amp; ſuch poore Romantique learning as would en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>force the antient worthyes both of art and courage to render a ſcornful bluſh to be ſeene amongſt ſuch but<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terflies, and to ſee ſuch unnatural and prepoſterous motion from perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, to imperfection, from rationali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,
<pb facs="tcp:45272:5"/>to meer animality or contradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctoriouſly; much reſembling the Dutchy of <hi>Spoleto</hi> in the territory of Narina (which according to <hi>Pliny</hi>) is exceeding dirty in a drought, and as duſty in wett weather, of ſuch ſort of ſtrang earth, were theſe <hi>Don Quixo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes</hi> compoſed; and having nothing to encourage their errant Knight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood but a poore leane <hi>Rozinante,</hi> or ſom gliſtering <hi>quoine</hi> of their fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fathers monuments which wil not paſſe currant with any (but weake Capacities) for others that obſerve their digreſſion from their Fathers virtues, cannot but conceave them better to have been piſt out againſt a <hi>Wind-Mill,</hi> then otherwiſe produced to the ſhame of their Genitors. If I ſhall ſeeme to much cenſorious, I ſhal earneſtly deſire a juſt cauſe of retraction, which wold be a Royal
<pb facs="tcp:45272:6"/>Cordial to all Princes and ſweet Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, which are perpetually moleſted with ſuch confident and inſolent ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>min, which wil ſtop the breach of any perſon that ſhal ſmel of honny (ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept they cloſe their Lipps &amp; Eares) againſt their entrance; If I have of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended in my deſcription of thoſ perſons, it wil be as difficult for me to recant, as for them to repent of their Rebellion, which is correſpondent to witchcraft, of which ſinne repented, I could never meete with an example except <hi>(Manaſſes)</hi> therefore doe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude their prudence to ſtand upon no other bottome, then the Diaboli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal attempt of greater Crimes; for al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though they know and have ſeene the cclipſcd beauty of heaven breake through ſuch darknes, to the enli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vening of all creatures againe, yet wil be, and are ſtil better enterteyned
<pb facs="tcp:45272:6"/>with ſuch Aegyptian darknes, though meaſured by a ſhort time, as moſt conducible to their black deſignes, conceaving this <hi>bonum preſens</hi> to be preferred bfore all notions of other Beatitude, or productioon of right rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon and nobleneſſe of ſoule, which demention, the heathen Poets have rendred a moſt certaine ſymptome of irrecoverable deſtruction, to which I leave them, and til then ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect it; what I have writt concerning the ſubſequent ſubject is for the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance of more reaſonable crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, as neereſt to the nature of the Gods, according to Poetical expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions delighted and refreſ hed with this <hi>Nectar.</hi> and if in this diſcourſe I cannot mount the capacity of hig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>her and more Gygantick reaſon, I ſhal entreate their aſſiſtance, for the better information of my ſelfe and
<pb facs="tcp:45272:7"/>the advantage of others, who cannot be better inſtructed at preſent by their humble and faithful Servant.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>To: Whitaker.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:45272:7"/>
            <head>THE BLOOD Of the GRAPE</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Lthough my inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is principally to explicate the <hi>juce</hi> of the <hi>Grape,</hi> yet I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but caſt a Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophycal glance upon <hi>Plants</hi> them ſelves as they are integraly, or in their parts helpeful or hurtful, preſerving the harmonie of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane nature by their <hi>homogeniali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,</hi> or forcing a diſcord by their <hi>he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terogeniality,</hi> ſuch therefore as in their integrality ſupport nature in its perpepual flux and reflux a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt <hi>Plants,</hi> are called in this tongue Pothearbs as <hi>Lettice, Cab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidge, VVatercreſſes</hi> and ſuch like, ſuch as are the parts of <hi>Plants</hi> are Rootes as <hi>Parſnips, Radish, Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rootes</hi> and <hi>Turnips,</hi> there are alſo
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:45272:8"/>ſome Plants which are ſpecifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally and by their univerſal tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per appropriated to particular parts of humane bodys, as <hi>Poeo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia, Betonica, Salvia, Verbaſculum,</hi> for the head; <hi>Crocus</hi> and <hi>Meliſſa,</hi> for the heart; <hi>Menta</hi> for the ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tricule; <hi>Eupatorium</hi> for the Liver; <hi>Capperes,</hi> for the ſpleene; and <hi>Hir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modactilus</hi> for the joints: There are other Plants alſo as pernitious to the whole body, or ſuch parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular parts, as <hi>Hyoſiamus</hi> for the head; <hi>Mezereon</hi> for the liver; <hi>Eruum</hi> for the rheins and bladder; <hi>Aloes,</hi> for the Hamorhoids. There are alſo a third ſort of Plants which are doubtful, and they are more or leſſe helpful to nature, as <hi>Colo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cynthis, Scamonium, Senna</hi> and theſe are adjuvants by reaſon of their Cathartique quality in ſeperating and educing corrupt humours from the incorrupt: There are
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:45272:8"/>alſo Plants more lignous, firme and indiſſoluble, as <hi>Oake,</hi> Appel and Peare-trees, and of this ſort ſome leſſe firme, as the <hi>Vine,</hi> which to deſect into its parts Containing and Contained, ſimilar and diſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milar, were a fruſtrate labour, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe every botomique hath pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed it more cleare and elegan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly then can be expected from my ſelfe. I shal render my Concep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions only of that ſimilar part of the <hi>Vine,</hi> which we cal liquid, and by Philoſophers underſtood <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,</hi> or <hi>Teares</hi> extracted from the Plant: This juce is the liquid part diffuſed in the ſubſtances of the Plants themſelves, which as their Blood conſerveth life in them, which bringeth me to my elect Subject, the <hi>Blood</hi> of the <hi>Grape,</hi> and as it appeareth to be blood, in it is life, 't is from the <hi>Vine,</hi> and that the Plant of life; and if the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:45272:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>difference between this Plant and the Tree of life in Paradiſe were but <hi>magis</hi> and <hi>minus</hi> 't is not ſo im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probable as to be rejected by any, for they wilbe both gra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted Plants of life, and they very much re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpond in their Nature as wel as Appellation: What the fruit was that ſprang from that in Paridice, is not as yet knowne, or not ſo perfectly underſtood, as that of the <hi>Vine,</hi> the Nature of which is ſo lively as that <hi>Galen</hi> wil affirme it to <hi>augment radical heate,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Galen: de Cauſſ: Morb: Cap: <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> which is the way to live for ever. <hi>Aſclepia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des</hi> the Phiſician telleth me, that this Blood doth conſent more with the nature of the Gods then any other, and that their Nature is incorrupt is without diſpute: ſecondly he adviſeth the uſe of it to unſound and infirme Conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutions, to reduce them to a firme and incorrupt temper, and accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:45272:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>to the ſenſe of <hi>Galen</hi> to aeter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity in this world; which cannot by any be underſtood of leſſe then an extreame extention of life, where it is properly or according to exact indication adhibited. howneceſſary then is the Study &amp; perpenſion of this ſubject, as a dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulty to explicate; neceſſary, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe our lives are short, and dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficult, becauſe Art is long and Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience dangerous; Yet if by this Act I shal be an inſtrument to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend life, and abreviate Art, not only shew the Plant, but teach the uſe, it may prove worth my la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour and acceptation of my <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thrauled Country,</hi> whoſe aſſurance shalbe that my beſt reaſon and Philoſophie shal be the guide of my pen: neither <hi>Hippocrates,</hi> nor <hi>Galen,</hi> or any other authority far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then I have digeſted them, and made them my owne reaſon
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:45272:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>and to agree with truth. As for the abreviation of Art, preſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Life, and reſtoring the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme, we shal comprehend in a ſmal Circle, and render in a few words, the ſumme of al Claſſick writers to this purpoſe, as the foureteene bookes of <hi>Galen</hi> his Method of curing and ſix of Health preſerving in theſe few words expreſt (viz.) <hi>Diet &amp; Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And by theſe two wayes prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipally are life and Health exten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded and reſtored. Quantity, qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity and the Mode of application in them obſerved. Quantity as it is <hi>uſque ad vaſa &amp; ad vires ſecundum juſtitiam</hi> rather then the ful capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city of the recipient, becauſe ſuch quantity of aliment muſt be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced into act by the power of Nature, which quantity to the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiention of the veſſels would pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ve
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:45272:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>burthen ſome, if not totally de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructive. Quality as it corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſponds with humane bodys uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſally, or with this, or that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dividual, the wel ordering of both requireth a juſt Conſideration of the recipient ſubject, as it may be exactly tempered, or valetudina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie; This terme Quantity of reth me a diſcourſe with <hi>Leſſius</hi> which ſeemeth to prefer a quantity <hi>ad pondus</hi> of Diet, as moſt conducing to the preſervation of health, and extention of Life, as if ſatiation were the usher of diſeaſes and mortality, as a corruptive Cauſe, which I cannot conceive reſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, nor can he render any Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument <hi>à teſtimonio</hi> but from his owne obſervation; which argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment <hi>à parti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ulari</hi> my <hi>Logique</hi> can not approve, nor wil it concurre with the Reaſon of others more reaſonable, to adhibite a ſtrict
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:45272:11"/>weight of aliment upon no occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion or difference of temper or di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtemper to be exceded or leſſened, nor can it be granted by any (ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept Religious) who wilfully and unreaſonably Chaſtiſe their Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies to merrit ſome thing beyond al intellect or reaſonable expreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, for in a phiſical ſenſe noe ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſt can embrace it otherwiſe then Heretical, if he wil ground his opinion upon the rule of <hi>Hip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrates</hi> and <hi>Gallen,</hi> ſcil: <hi>Contraria contrarijs curantur,</hi> that Diſeaſes are recovered by their contraries as inanition by faſting muſt be reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered by repletion in feeding; and this inanition may be extream or not. &amp; in ſuch condition no ſever pondus or weight can be obſerved for although inanition muſt be replenished, yet it muſt be effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted by repetition often of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coctible aliment, in more or leſſe
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:45272:11"/>quantity according to the conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient power of the parts reci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pient, as for the quality of the ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment according to the rule of <hi>ijs nutrimur quibus conſtamus</hi> muſt be <hi>Homogeneal</hi> for the ſupport of uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal nature as wel as the recove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of each morbid individual and in this poynt the auntients have been obſerved exceeding ſtrict and as they had great reaſon ſoe is the judgment of any Phiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian moſt ſeene and cenſured by his election of aliment in quality agreable to the temper of body, for although an effect muſt be cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by its contrary, yet the right temper muſt be ſupported by its owne ſimile, as heate by heate and moyſture by moyſture, but whither in degree more or leſſe moyſt or intenſe, is indicated by the natural conſtitution of that body and to be ordered by the
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:45272:12"/>Phiſitian, but this is a Paradox ot not underſtood by vulgar practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers who argue falſely upon this true ground of <hi>Hyppocrates,</hi> ſo ſuch as accept his <hi>Contraria contrarijs cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantur</hi> to be a rule without excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in nourishing as much as cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, as if there were noe differen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce betweene contrary, and contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, Rebellion and Loyalty, 't is truth as remedies they muſt be contrary to the affect and thus <hi>Ariſt:</hi> will have a crooked Plant bent as much the other way to ſtraiten it, but if a ſtraite Plant shalbe incurvated there wil be conſequently an organical affect, which wee call <hi>vitiata figura,</hi> ſo al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo if contrarie remedies or quale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties shalbe applyed to an harmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius temper, it wil be a cauſe effi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient of diſcord &amp; conflict in natu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re or in the fore ſaid temper, ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is apparent, that the quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:45272:12"/>is more to be obſerved either in meate or Medicine then the quantity (eſpecially of aliment) becauſe natural choice of foode is in noe Creature of health <hi>ultra ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacitatem recipientis,</hi> but if any <hi>Leſſian</hi> shall diſpute as ſtrictly for temperance according to his mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, I muſt ſeverally as a Phiſitian tel them the Worthies of our Art preferreth exceſs before ſuch tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perance, for they affirme Canoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally that al affects or diſeaſes of plentitude or fulneſſe are more ſafe becauſe more curable then diſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of Emptineſſe, and who doth not apprehend variety of reaſon in this <hi>axiome,</hi> firſt becauſe univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal evacuation is ſooner effected then repletion; Secondly, becauſe accidents of various formes can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be avoyded for they are infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite, and the leaſt affliction upon an extenuate and leſſiate body, for
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:45272:13"/>defect of excrementitious hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours to involue them, giveth a dangerous charge to the radical principles, becauſe both the diſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe and medicine having nothing elſe to encounter muſt tyranniſe over enfeebled nature as by its owne impotency not able to reſiſt which Conatus naturae or endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vor to expel noctious cauſes doth over heate the ſpirits and effect ſuch preternatural heate by its motion from the Center to the Circumference as doth inflame natural heate according to Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtophorus a vega and not other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe by the aſcent of putrid fuli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginous vapours to the Heart ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to vulgar opinion; Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarily, where there is a ſufficiencie of excrementitious humours to entertaine both the Diſeaſe and Remedy, there are they retained with leſſe oppreſſion and danger
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:45272:13"/>to the radical ſpirits, and removed with leſſe offence to the univerſal temper of the perſon ſo labouring as wil be more Phyloſophically demonſtrated according to this ſubſequent mode. <hi>Albertus,</hi> and many other Philoſophers doe conſtitute in mixt Bodys a two fold Moyſture: one which they nominate <hi>humidum continuans</hi> and from this continuating hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>midity the Iunction of parts doth proceed, otherwiſe they would be al ſiccity, and conſequently upon any motion diſunited; therefore there is no natural Body void of this Humidity, though never ſo hard or grave, as is dayly demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrated by every <hi>Chymical Operator,</hi> every hower extracting oyle out of the hardeſt body; Therefore this Humidity is by Phyſitians nominated <hi>Oleaginoſum humidum</hi> an oyley moiſture, conſiſting of
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:45272:14"/>ayrie and aqueous moyſture.</p>
            <p>The other humidity being <hi>hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>midum quaſi nutriens</hi> is a waterish moiſture in the mixt body, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing advantagious to the conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuation of parts, &amp; becauſe of its tenuity is eaſily reſolved which cannot with ſuch facility be effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted upon the <hi>Oleaginous,</hi> becauſe of its craſſitude or thickneſſe, ſoe that were a proportion of excre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentitious humours is wanting in a body by reaſon of a ſevere or thin Diet, in that body both di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſe, and medicine muſt of neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity be more tyrannicall over the fixed moyſture, which is the liga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of life; and for this cauſe all Phiſitians will acknowledge Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſes of fulneſſe admitt of a more ſafe and ſpeedy cure then thoſe of inanition, as diſeaſes alſoe of a cold quality admit of a more ſafe remedy then hot diſtempers, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:45272:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>in the application of hot re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medies to the former we foment natural heat, and our cold appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations to the other, we doe not only debilitate, but very often ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinguiſh naturall heàt. But be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I intend noe Controverſy, I shal fix my ſelfe upon my pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per ſubject, and ſhew how every temper may be preſerved void of all diſtempers, proceeding from the material principles of nature by the uſe of <hi>Wine,</hi> and alſo prove it to be an excellent and ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fical remedy, in all affects produ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced by the diſcord of the foreſaid Principles, being peritely applyed according to proper indication, nor shal I be prolix in my tracta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of all the parts of this diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe. Curioſity and expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion will proove abhortive, if a taſte of this promiſed <hi>Iuyce</hi> be not ſuddainely preſented, whoſe
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:45272:15"/>nature and excellency hath and doth appeare in our former ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions, to be <hi>Encomiaſtick</hi> ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient, and ſuch excellent Nectar in the opinion of <hi>Noah,</hi> that he made it is firſt Act of Husbandry after the Deluge to Plant a <hi>vinyard,</hi> before any other fruite or grayne, as is affirmed by ſacred Teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny: The reaſon of that act, if I should preſume to render or ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicate that Text, without better quallification, I might not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out cauſe, from <hi>Theologiſts,</hi> have thrown upon me that ſnuff of <hi>Ne ſutor ultra crepidam;</hi> yet can I not ſoe much inthrall my fancy, or ſuffocate ſuch notions as may be probable though not an abſolute and perfect Demonſtration, as to paſſe by his firſt act after his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection, or not to take notice of his age, which I find extended twenty yeares beyond the age of
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:45272:15"/>
               <hi>Adam,</hi> in whom the Principles of nature according to my reaſon &amp; ſenſe should have been moſt pure and durable: Nor can I argue o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe, but that matter ſoe for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med muſt be ſubject to dayly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caye by perpetuall motion, there fore how <hi>Noah</hi> after ſoe many Centuries from <hi>Adam</hi> should in age extend twenty yeares longer can make noe impreſſion in my reaſon: (the taſte of this <hi>Nectar</hi> excepted) which is (I conceive) an inferior ſpeties of that <hi>Plant</hi> of <hi>Life</hi> from which <hi>Adam</hi> was exclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, for had it been of equall or the ſame perfection, whereas he lived after his Plantation Three Hundred and fifty yeares (which was a good <hi>Cordiall</hi>) yet he had now been living and eternall in this world, but as a beſt ſecond was proved by his own experien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce, and by ſix hundred yeares ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:45272:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>he could not but be ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently taught how to frame reaſonable arguments to ſatisfy both himſelfe and others; and by reducing it into its principles, make a ſenſible diſcoverie of natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res miſtery and upon ſuch like experimental obſervation did he plant his <hi>Vinyard:</hi> ſo that by infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence the excellency of this ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jectt doth appeare more tranſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent then any other Iuyce either of vegitall or Animal: Therefore it shalbe my next conſideration, to explicate the nature of it, with its difference and uſe, both in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of aliment and Medicament and with its application to every individual, of every age, and tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per; therefore that we may act as much as we ſpeake, let us looke upon the quality of <hi>Wine</hi> Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phically; and at the firſt view we shall diſcover a two fold heat in
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:45272:16"/>it, as it iſſueth from a living body (Viz.) an animall and elemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary heat, for though <hi>Wine</hi> can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be ſaid to be <hi>animatum,</hi> ſuch as giveth a ſoul or life; yet it may carry with it, and to its ſelfe the Impreſſion of a centrall or im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>planted heat from a ſoule as may playnely be demonſtrated in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther things; as the ſeed of Ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mals or of plants, have not a ſoule in act according to the Doctrine of <hi>Ariſtotel;</hi> Yet it doth take from a ſoule ſuch a generative power like unto the ſoule, which (<hi>Ariſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tel</hi> ſaith) is nothing elſe, but a vital heat diſtinct from igneous and elementary; ſoe as in the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration of a living Creature the firſt moving is Animal, or the Plant from which the ſeed iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſueth, but the ſeed is the inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment which by a power of vitalli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty receaved from the Plant beget<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:45272:17"/>another beeing like it ſelfe; ſince therefore there is <hi>in ſemine,</hi> a vitall heat diſtinct from elemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary, why may we not affirme the ſame of <hi>Wine,</hi> which in like man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner iſſueth from an animate body; then wil <hi>Wine</hi> appeare to have a double heat, or one conflate or moved out of two, and that which is great and intenſe doth not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt of an indiviſible, becauſe it is greater or leſſe according to the variety of ſpecies, and diverſity of ſituation or places; for in thoſe Regions where the ſun effects a ſtronger heat, there grow hotter <hi>Wines,</hi> &amp; this heat is not external, but rather naturall and implanted in the <hi>Wine</hi> becauſe from the heat of the place, the vital and elemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary heat, which conſtituteth the natural heat of the <hi>Wine,</hi> doth be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come more great and intenſe; nor can it be denyed, in <hi>Wine</hi> to be a
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:45272:17"/>double moyſture according to <hi>Gallen;</hi> who diſtinguisheth the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance <hi>Vinoſa,</hi> from the ſubſtance <hi>Aquoſa,</hi> the <hi>qualitas vinoſa,</hi> being that humidity inherent which doth unite the parts, &amp; the wate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rish ſubſtance, is only that which is contracted from aliment: for ſoe long as the <hi>Grape</hi> was conjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to the <hi>Vine,</hi> there did flow there unto a waterish humour by which it was nourished, and after 'tis ſeparated from the <hi>Vine,</hi> doth ſtil retaine that waterish humour, which as then was not converted, nor aſſimulated into the ſubſtance of <hi>Wine;</hi> nor can it have any fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther converſion, becauſe the wine is now noe more <hi>animatum,</hi> or able to produce it into Act; and this is that humidity in Wine which is ſpent or waſted in boyling, the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther remayneth which is innate &amp; fixed to the ſubſtance of Wine,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:45272:18"/>and hence it is that the boyling of <hi>Wine</hi> doth render it more ſweete; for by the expence of this humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dity the juyce returneth to its owne naturall moiſture; And this (I hope) wilbe ſatisfaction con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Generall nature of <hi>Wine:</hi> which familiarity with hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayne nature wil appeare; the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of all <hi>Wines</hi> being either <hi>corro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berative</hi> &amp; <hi>nutritive</hi> or <hi>mundificative,</hi> or <hi>apperative,</hi> and theſe are not only teſtifyed by the antient and learned <hi>Phiſitians;</hi> but proved out of their own exiſtence &amp; prime animation; which wilbe here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after demonſtrated, in our pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſe; therefore we cannot but take notice of the diſtinction of <hi>Wines</hi> by their names and colours. Concerning their difference in names, they are ſovarious, as to render them in all their appella<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, will rellish more of curioſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:45272:18" rendition="simple:additions"/>then utility: many of them being fantaſtically impoſed by the wanton ſingularity in Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants of al Nations; but ſoe many as <hi>Philoſophers, Phiſitians</hi> and <hi>Poets</hi> have notefied, I shall briefly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare and then paſſe to their Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours. In the firſt place let us take notice of the General name <hi>vinum</hi> and ſoe denominated <hi>à vi, &amp; vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cendo,</hi> from the power and ſtrength of it, according to <hi>Varro;</hi> and I ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der it <hi>vinum quaſi divinum,</hi> and ſoe the pleaſant <hi>Nectar</hi> of the <hi>Gods;</hi> the antients had many ſorts different in name, as <hi>Fortinum,</hi> newly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſt from the Grape, <hi>Protopum,</hi> ſuch as fell from the <hi>Vyne</hi> before the Grapes were trodden; Others which take their names from the Region in which they grow; As <hi>Chium, Lesbium, Falernum, Cacubum, Surrentinum, Caelenum, Signinum, Tarraconenſe, Spoletinum, Ceretanum,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:45272:19"/>Fundanum, Malvaticum;</hi> Amongſt the <hi>French</hi> many others, as <hi>Vinum Remenſe, burdegalenſe, Aurelianenſe Belonenſe, Divionenſe, Montiſpedo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nenſe;</hi> And theſe agree better, (as Table Drinkes) with ſound bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dys, then infirme conſtitutions, there are more debile and dilute wines in <hi>France</hi> which agree better with <hi>febrile</hi> diſpoſitions, then with cold <hi>Phlegmatick</hi> tempers; As <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſienſe, Limonicenſe, Forenſe, Alobro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genſe,</hi> with many others, and ſince both their names are knowne, and their natures in parte, and ſuch tempers to which they are moſt concenient, let us take a taſte, and principally peirce theſe foure veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels, (Viz.) <hi>Sweet, accute, Auſtere,</hi> and <hi>Milde,</hi> obſerving their colours (Viz.) <hi>White, Sanguineus, Yellow</hi> and <hi>Black;</hi> the firſt three common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly knowne to us by their names of <hi>White, Claret</hi> and <hi>Sack;</hi> and theſe admitt of their differences; for as
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:45272:19"/>there are ſeveral ſorts of <hi>Sack</hi> and <hi>claret,</hi> ſoe are there alſoe of <hi>White Wines,</hi> ſome <hi>Sweet,</hi> ſome <hi>Auſtere,</hi> ſome <hi>thick,</hi> others <hi>limped</hi> and <hi>cleere,</hi> and all theſe pure nutritives; but inferior in degree of nourishing to ſuch as are ſweet; And although <hi>Dulcia Maxime nutriunt</hi> muſt be with this caution, that the <hi>Liver, Spleene</hi> and <hi>Reynes</hi> be void of ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, which becauſe they ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally obteyn a body more craſſe, they are ſaid to obſtruct; Thusha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving breifly &amp; Philoſophically de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſected their bodyes and preferred their nature &amp; ſpecifical differen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce to publique view, I shal preſent them to a medicall conſideration.</p>
            <p>The quallityes generally re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived by all <hi>Phiſitians,</hi> are neutri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive and they doe nouriſh <hi>ſuper omnia alimenta,</hi> if <hi>Gallen:</hi> may have credit: becauſe <hi>Wine</hi> is <hi>ſemi ſanguis,</hi> or halfe blood, before it be recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:45272:20"/>and produced into act with a leſſe fire of nature, and leaves be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind it no excrement, as all other <hi>vegitalls</hi> and <hi>animalls</hi> doe; it doth alſo evacuate both <hi>ſurſum &amp; deor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum</hi> upward and downeward; it doth corrobarate all faculties, <hi>at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tractive, retentive, concoctive</hi> and <hi>di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtributive;</hi> it doth correct putrefa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction; open obſtructions; <hi>&amp; exhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerat</hi> the ſpirits; what more is now requiſite or needfull for preſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or reſtoration of health and life, then this ſo familiar to the principles of humayne bodyes, and ſo undoubtedly knowne, in moſt Regions, and incomparable with any other <hi>vegitall,</hi> or <hi>minerall</hi> (eſpecially) <hi>mineralls,</hi> whoſe natur is deſtructive and <hi>Heterogeneall</hi> to all animalls? who according to Philoſophicall obſervation <hi>non patitur afflictionem</hi> which cannot be avoyded in them, becauſe their
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:45272:20"/>preparation conſiſteth of a juſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giment of fire; which was ſo hard to be gained by <hi>Iohannis Crato,</hi> that for that uncertainty inſteed of his <hi>Chimicall Tutor</hi> he choſe a <hi>Galleneſt;</hi> And my ſelfe have obſerved very exact <hi>Chimiſts,</hi> whoſe medicines of the ſame kind, and prepared with as much dilligence as poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble; ſometimes ſo gentle, as chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren would not complaine; and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine ſoe violent, as the ſtrongeſt nature could not ſuſteyne; which much confirmed my opinion with <hi>Crato</hi> of the difficulties to ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect that juſt Regiment of fier; and if we be curious in our ſcrutation we ſhal finde alſo much, if not ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reconcileable difference in other drugs <hi>Galenicall,</hi> both in figure and operation: eſpecially ſuch as are tranſported from other Regions, which I dare affirm are not known to us according to their natural
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:45272:21"/>perfection, and though the uſe of them be doubtfull, yet frequent, and if we doe know them, either we cannot have them, or ſuch is their change and alteration in tranſportation as doth force us to blame the antients for their high applauſe of them, we not finding in the applicaton of them accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to proper ſcope, and indica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion any ſuch excellency; and if any will credit <hi>Chriſtophorus Barri</hi> (the <hi>Ieſuite</hi>) in his Relation of <hi>Cohinchina</hi> to his Holy Father the <hi>Pope,</hi> to whom he doth proteſt that the <hi>Rhubarbe</hi> he brought from thence with many other Drugs, were ſo altered in their tranſpor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, as without a ſpecial ſcript upon them, he could not have knowne them to be the ſame ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in virtue, or colour; and that learned and expert moderne (<hi>Sym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phorianus</hi>) doth challeng moſt of
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:45272:21"/>our <hi>Pharmacall Compoſitions</hi> upon the ſame ground and doth affirme the chiefe ingredients to be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowne or found in the ſhops of <hi>Europian Apothecaries,</hi> for better ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction accept his owne words, <hi>ſed quod res quaſdam vel non afferis, vel non ſine maculâ, vel in totum ignorari puto: ea ſunt Balſamum, Cardamomum, Myrrha, Nardus Indica, Caffia, ſcordium, Cinnamomum, Radix Pentaphilli, Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamus Ordoratus, Xylobalſomum.</hi> This Challenge I ſuppo2e will be diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cult to anſwer by the perpenders: what ſhall we then ſay to the great incertainty of the moſt grand Compoſitions in our <hi>Phar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macopea?</hi> but that with them we do <hi>pugnare contra hoſtem clauſis ocu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis.</hi> I could raiſe many Diſputes upon other things much in uſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt us, and their incertainety of their virtues; beſides the non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſatisfaction of their entity accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:45272:22"/>to vulgar opinion, and ſuch different deſcriptions, as have ben divulged; as <hi>Vnicornes-horne, Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zoardſtone,</hi> and ſuch like: but my intention is rather to be taught, then controvert, or elſe to inform others; for which cauſe I have undertaken the tractation of this ſubject: the <hi>Plant</hi> and <hi>Iuyce</hi> there of being ſo wel knowne to al Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and ſenſible without con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſie to all reaſonable Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, and uſed in all places with reſpect to their ſpeciall difference, from the wombe, which nouri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheth and produceth them; and if I ſhal not more clearely manifeſt the foreſaid Qualities to be in it, and by the Conſultations of more learned, then my ſelfe, then ſhal I in no manner give ſo full ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction to the expectator; There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that which was laſt in my in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention, ſhalbe firſt in execution;
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:45272:22" rendition="simple:additions"/>and though I render not an Index of Authors, yet my ſubſequent Arguments ſhal be from teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny; not doubting to cleare our opinion to the full extenſion of ſuch argumentation, and after this Dialecticall forme to cleere the Point.</p>
            <p>The firſt then is, that <hi>Wyne</hi> nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſheth above all other aliment; They who have had acquaintance with <hi>Galen:</hi> know they are his words tranſlated; and that ſome nouriſh more or leſſe, according to their ſpecial quality, as <hi>Vina a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quea per exiguum alimentum corpori praebent, quae verò craſſa ſunt et colore rubra, plus alimenti habent quam reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qua vina. Galen.</hi> Secondly, that it doth corroborate: <hi>Vinum confortat ſpiritum, &amp; in ſpiritum convertitur, &amp; fortificat virtutem; Avicen:</hi> Thirdly that it doth evacuate; <hi>Vina craſſa dulciaque quod alvum deijciant nemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:45272:23" rendition="simple:additions"/>ferà ignotum eſt; ſicut multum quod tametſi aegrè concoquatur craſſumque ſuccum &amp; inflationes faciat, alvum ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men movet: Galen.</hi> Fourthly, that it doth open obſtruction: <hi>Vinum dul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce vehementer apperit oppilationes pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monis. Avicen:</hi> Laſtly, that it doth exhilerate the ſpirits, is proved by ſacred teſtimony, <hi>Scil: Vinum cor hominis exhilerat.</hi> Thus have I Briefly rendred a confirmation of the a foreſaid qualities medically in <hi>Wine;</hi> and Iuſtified them by an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient and orthodox authoritie; Notwithſtanding for further ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisafaction, let us caſt our eye up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon the qualitie of <hi>Wines</hi> as they are obviouſly di2courſed in groſſe by moſt or all the prime Aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tients, <hi>Scil: White Wine</hi> may be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibited in all <hi>acute</hi> and <hi>hot</hi> diſtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers <hi>ut voluit Hippocrates; ſweet Wine</hi> in cold diſeaſes; becauſe it heateth the body more, <hi>ſed calefa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctione
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:45272:23"/>temperatâ Galen:</hi> no white <hi>Wine</hi> is ſweet, and ſuch as is pure and ſubtile moveth urine ſtren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uouſly, without any impreſſion in the head, becauſe it doth not ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſtly heat, but ſenſibly refrige<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate and is ordained in <hi>febre conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuâ, Galen; Wyne</hi> in Generall mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derately uſed doth purge choler by urine, exhilarate the minde, and refreſ heth the ſenſes; <hi>Wyne</hi> alſo that is dilute may ſafely and profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tably be adhibited in an Apoze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>micall forme in fevers; as will ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare in our ſubſequent tractation of particular, and moſt grand diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempers; <hi>White Wine</hi> doth ſenſibly refrigerate and cleanſe the Lungs, &amp; one Drought doth Extinguiſh thirſt more then one gallon of barly water; as my owne experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence for many yeares, and in many hundred perſons can affirme; ſweet wines alſo may be adhibited in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:45272:24"/>paſſions as <hi>pleuriſies</hi> and <hi>infla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation</hi> of the lungs, to provoke <hi>expectoration,</hi> when the matter is di2geſted according to <hi>Oribatius, Haliabbas, Conſtantius Monachus, Wyne</hi> alſo that is white, ſubtile, and thinne, is not turbulent to the <hi>ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tricle,</hi> but of eaſie digeſtion, ſoone penetrates the veines, provoketh urine, and leaveth no excrement, as doth all other <hi>vegitals</hi> or <hi>Ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mals</hi> and <hi>minorals;</hi> And as before ſaid that it doth in all hot diſtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers Extinguish thirſt, is the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation alſoe of <hi>Iſaac</hi> the Sonne of <hi>Solomon</hi> an <hi>Arabian King;</hi> Laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly white <hi>Wine</hi> is ſaid to be inſipide dilut, coagulate by its frigiditie <hi>in ſe;</hi> Yet under favour in reſpect of its univerſal parts, there can be no ſuch <hi>Coagulation,</hi> as is affirmed by <hi>Iohannes Portugalenſis once Pope of Rome;</hi> Theſe are the univerſall o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinions of the Ancients; yet the
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:45272:24"/>reaſon of the reader may exact a more demonſtrative proofe of ſuch contraritie in the ſame body of ſo pure a nature, as to open and cloſe, to corroborate and debili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate, and that theſe contrarie acts should appeare at the ſame time, in the ſame ſubject to whome it is Applyed, as that <hi>Wine,</hi> as you have heard, should generally Evacuate <hi>Excreme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>titious</hi> humors of the body or particularly purge <hi>bilious</hi> Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter by Urine and yet the ſame ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifical <hi>Wine</hi> shall corroborate the whole and everie part it worketh upon at the ſame time; for al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though everie perfect body be mixed of the principles of rarety, denſity and graetie, yet if their shal be the addition of one other digeſtion they will ſeperate in themſelves, and levitie wil not ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare as levitie and gravetie in the ſame ſpheare; as wine doth af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:45272:25"/>the addition of ſeveral dige<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions, more then is received from the plant in its mixture; and though there are occult qualities of which no other profe can be made, then ſuch an illogicall argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment as is Framed <hi>à particulari;</hi> or that it doth worke ſoe; yet when I contemplate the ſupernatural per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection of mixture in this <hi>plant,</hi> Exceedinge and comprehending all other <hi>Vegitals</hi> and <hi>Minerals</hi> as doth appeare by its puretie in na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, which as gold will nor doth receive any, but a ſeeming corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; but Exceeding gold in its familiaritie which humane com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plection, and the Complement or Epitome of all other plants; as Man is in his forme, and mixture the short repreſentative of the great world; And as we are ſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and knowing theſe qualeties to be in <hi>Wine</hi> ſoe wil they appeare
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:45272:25"/>with as litle contradictio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as thoſe of inferiour <hi>Plants, Scil: Guiacum,</hi> which doth by conſtringing eva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuate, as is more manifeſt in the ſqueeſzing of a <hi>ſpung:</hi> or <hi>Rhubarb,</hi> which doth conſtring by purge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, others will have a catholi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que and incorruptible ſpirit in wine exceeding all ſuch mixtures; &amp; that it moveth as a free Agent in its ſphear of activitie; and for sthis reaſon hath Phyloſophers &amp; Poets ſuppo2ed it to participate wth the nature of the <hi>Gods,</hi> which muſt move as liberall agents; It may alſo in more plane phyloſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phie appeare to move after ſuch manner by virtue of its fluent &amp; fixt heat, the one oleaginous continuating, binding and vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the parts together, the other fluent attenuating the humors, and looſening the belly or body univerſally, and thus probably to
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:45272:26"/>effect ſuch contrary actions out of its natural mixture, ſince there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it can and doth operate in ſuch manner, there is much rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon it ſhould be thus uſed, no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther vegital or mineral ſo pleaſant or perfectly concocted, (except gold) nor any ſo familiar to hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Nature all other fruits, and juces beeing more ſubject to pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trefaction or ſuch like alteration, and more onerous to nature in concoction, and by reaſon of their leſſe perfect concoction, moſt of them breeding litle blood, or vitious blood or none at all; but wine, eſpecially red wine, is halfe blood before it be received; and when I find the Antients, nomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate it, <hi>the old mans milk,</hi> they muſt grant it a ſuper — concoction to blood, as it is cited <hi>in jecore;</hi> for milke is blood dealbated, &amp; ſuch as have received a more perfect
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:45272:26"/>concoction, then it hath in the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver; And for its encomiaſticke, it is the Medicine that ſeteth a true edge upon nature, ſupporteth an appetite in being, and recovereth it languiſhing; And where as <hi>me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicamentum</hi> is defined, to bee a <hi>me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dium</hi> betweene poyſon &amp; aliment, and by conſequence muſt leave af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter operation ſome venemous contact; this Medicine is ſo diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent in operation, as that it lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth a lively contact, and becauſe of its univerſall <hi>homogenialitie</hi> with nature, cannot be compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended under the diffinition of <hi>medicamentum,</hi> though ſo nomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, becauſe a true diffinition doth explicate the nature and Eſſence of the thing defined, yet that it is a medicine, and under ſuch notion apprehended the practiſe of <hi>Avi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenna, Rhaſis,</hi> and <hi>Averroes</hi> juſtify, when themſelv's uſed twice every
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:45272:27"/>month to move their body's with the ſame either <hi>ſurſum vel deorſum,</hi> or both; And if my owne obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation may be acceptable then I cannot conceale ſuch powerfull Effects as my ſelfe hath felt, and ſeen in others; <hi>Scil:</hi> conſumptive and extenuate bodyes reſtored to a ſarcocity, and from withered Bodys to fresh, plumpe, fat and fleshie; and from old and infirme to young, and ſtrong; when as wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter or ſmall beare Drinkers were countenanced more like <hi>Apes</hi> then <hi>Men;</hi> and if I had no other reaſon but my own experience it were Enough to ingage my faith, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning its excellencie. My eye now is converted upon the vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar, and find their pulſe in a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordred Motion, their hearts being preternaturally dilated with the reporte of preſervation from death, ſickneſſe, and payne, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:45272:27"/>Natural death and extreem old age ſuffereth diſſolution with out any payne, and all theſe to be effected with a medicine ſo fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar, as no longer they can for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bear the proverb, <hi>that he that is not now a phyſition muſt be dubed for a foole;</hi> But let ſuch apprehenſions be carefull of the right applica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of this <hi>Medicament,</hi> leaſt the title be inverted upon themſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ves, for the difference of tempers, diſtempers, times &amp; clymes, with circu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtance of ſex, wil exerciſe the beſt <hi>Hippocratiſt</hi> or Phyloſopher rightly to order and aply this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medie; for cauſes externall of Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancholie are more frequent in <hi>Aethiopia,</hi> then any other region, the aire being cold and dry, and the time principaly in which this humer doth Moue is the Autume. Though <hi>Hippocrates</hi> will have the ſpring to have precedence, yet I
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:45272:28"/>underſtand the affect the be gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated in either, but propagated through the whole body in the winter; ſo that theſe circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces neglected and the remedie contrarie to proper indication or ignorantly adviſed, the princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of nature muſt ſuffer abbre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viation in ſtead of Extenſion; <hi>Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pericks</hi> ſtand here like the fiction of <hi>Tantalus,</hi> the fruit is not only <hi>in conſpectu,</hi> but with in the ſpace of their graſp, yet deprived of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tact, they may ſee this ſubject tranſcending their logick from a particular to a univerſal; Nor can they argue from experience who know not what they doe, in every one of theſe following reſpects, which are beyond the capacity of an <hi>Emperick, quatenus Emperick;</hi> Yet before I proceed in the fore ſaid reſpects, give me leave to ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute <hi>Plato,</hi> who hath tackt me with
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:45272:28"/>aprohibition concerning Kings, Magiſtrates, ſoldiers, woemen and ſervants, to whom he abſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tely prohibiteth the uſe of <hi>wine</hi> in any Region, or at any time, as if hee would appropriate this felici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie only to the Commonweale of ſchollers; but upon farther per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſion wee cannot but returne a candid interpretation; for doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe hee intended principally ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brietie, not forbidding the mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate uſe of <hi>wine</hi> to any ſuch perſon before named, otherwiſe he muſt deprive them of the refreshment of ſpirit, and the generation of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corrupt humors; which hath prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal relation to all the faculties, both naturall, vital, and animal; &amp; if notice be taken of the Exceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive operation of this juce, kings wilbe verrie ſenſible of its adju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancie in their election of officers and ſervants of all conditions, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:45272:29"/>it openeth the cloſeſt locks, and diſcovers the moſt good or evil intentions; all exceſſe wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king upon the ſubject according to its diſpoſition or predominan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce of humor; And no Tyron will deny the behaviour of men to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree with their various Comple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xions, nor that the ſame ſpeciſick, <hi>wine</hi> doth irradiate it ſelfe with as much varietie, as are their indivi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dual perſons; as a candle ſet up in a lanthern compoſed of various Coloured glaſſe <hi>ſcil:</hi> white, red greene, blew, black, yellow, or any other mixt Coulor, the Irradia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion through every one of theſe of the foreſaid lamp, wil corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpond or anſwer the complection of each particular glaſſe; And the Dutch make it a rule of politicks, by which they ſteere their courſe of al contracts by it, and will not conclude any bargaine before
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:45272:29"/>they ſee the ſpirit of <hi>wine</hi> operate, for feare of ſome concealed ſnake under the hearbes; And doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe the moderat uſe of <hi>wine,</hi> for the animation of the ſoldiers, the inlivening of the Magiſtrate, and recoverie of women, is profitable, Eſpecially in <hi>hyſtericall</hi> ſits; accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to <hi>Hippocrates.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hipp: I denatura Mulie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum</note> And my tranſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion now ſhall be to the tempers of humane bodyes in generall, &amp; the wynes generally agreeing with thoſe tempers; and then more particularly to this or that individual. Temper it ſelfe beeing the reaſon of mixture, or the har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony and conſent of the prime qualities in Elements, and by the Exuberancie of each ſimple qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, theſe foure ſymple tempers are created; as hot, when the heat predominateth over the cold, and yet of ſiccity and moiſture remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth an equallity; and ſo of the
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:45272:30"/>reſt, as cold, dry and moiſt, beſides theſe foure conjugate tempers, which proceed from the exube<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rancy of the two firſt qualities, as hot and moiſt, hot and dry, cold and moiſt, cold and dry, which are the foure compound tempers, their fixation conſiſting in that <hi>oleaginous</hi> humour, which wee call <hi>innatum calidum;</hi> and this innate ſo utile, and neceſſary, as a cauſe with out which mixt bodys cannot ſubſiſt; 't is alſo fomented and ſupported by fluent heat contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted in the heart, veines and Arte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, as their <hi>proper Channels</hi> conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting of ſpirituall blood preſerved in the heart, as the middle of the body, which by a lively conſent doth maintaine &amp; ſupport innate heat, and perfect the univerſal temper of the body, even as the Sun inliveneth, and inlightne h the great world, ſo doth the heart
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:45272:30"/>ejaculate a fluent heat to the vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſication of the <hi>microcoſine,</hi> or lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle world of humane bodys, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freshing every part, and exciting every particular function to its proper motion; ſo as the innate or fixt ſpirit doth very much reſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pond the fluent, and ſuch reſipro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call concordance is as neceſſary as circulation in the ſun, whoſe mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion being ſtopt, or influence ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinguiſhed but one hower, would be the ruine of the whole world; and if ſuch a cauſe may be admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, as ſome call <hi>cauſa ſine quâ non,</hi> then this comerce between fluent and fixt heat may be ſo accepted, for otherwiſe all naturall actions are quiet and extinct: therefore theſe beeing the prime exiſtence and ſubſiſtence of humane nature, and ſuch powerfull agents in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation and nutrition, their ſpheare of motion may be more
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:45272:31"/>or leſſe adapted by external mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, either <hi>homogeniall</hi> or <hi>heteroge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neall;</hi> And for tempers or diſtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers in generall there can be no a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liment or medicament ſo conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient and agreeable as <hi>wine;</hi> for the ſmalleſt <hi>wine</hi> (if pure) is a more neat &amp; clear <hi>pabulum,</hi> to the fluent ſpirits, then recent egges, or milke ſucked from any creature; they all onerating nature with ſome ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crement after concoction, and in concoction muſt be ſome expence both of fluent and fixt heart, which is ſo much an abbreviation to a naturall beeing, but is of ſuch puretie and ſpirituality, as doth receive a ſudden mutation, and in its alteration addeth both light &amp; heat to the foreſaid principles, as the oyl of thoſe natural lampes. <hi>Fernelius</hi> apprehendeth much dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger either in meat or medicine, which are onerous to the princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:45272:31"/>of nature; and therefore will have all cold diſeaſes admit of a more ſafe remedie, then hot diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempers, becauſe in the regular way of cureing by contraries, the application of hot remedies to cold affects doth foment &amp; main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine naturall heat, contrarily in the application of cold remedies in hot diſtempers, to extinguiſh preternatural heart; the naturall heate doth ſuffer much and many tymes is extinct with praeternaturall or febrill heat; but in both cold and hot affects the application of <hi>wine</hi> upon pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per indication, is the moſt Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent and in ofenſive remedie. And that it is ſuch a remedy, I shal pro duce ſom probable Arguments to make it more apparant to vulger intellects, after this ſubſequent mode. If it were by the moſt lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Auntients in Medicine adhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bited,
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:45272:32"/>as a ſafe remedy in fevers, then it acounted proper in hot diſtempers, for thus it hath been adminiſtered by them, as hath been demonſtrated in our former diſcourſe, and wilbe more appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant in our following of the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular and moſt grand affects of humane bodyes; And if it hath alſo been derected and ordained by the ſame authoritie in cold di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtempers, then it is a proper re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medie and approved in both; And if we perpend the ſpecifical diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences of <hi>wines,</hi> then wee shal ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke it a regular remedie according to the rule of Contrariety; for <hi>Wyne</hi> that is generous moveth in all tempers from the Centure to the circumference; and other <hi>Wy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes</hi> in their proper nature more apperient, open obſtructions, and in a <hi>Galenicall</hi> ſenſe all oppilations are efficient cauſes of putrefaction
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:45272:32"/>and putrefaction of fevers; ſo that opening being a contrary mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to obſtruction, <hi>Wine</hi> is a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie remedie <hi>per ſe</hi> in oppilation <hi>Et per accidens</hi> in putrid fevers; Now I shal deſcend to particular and difficult effects controverted amongſt the Moſt learned, and where I find them differ in this poynt, shal endeavour to recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cile them, for the ſatiſfaction of greener ſtudents, and practicers leſs perite which after induſtrie wil effect; not but his underta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, would better become a more learned pen and Perſon of a more ſettled condition, then a perſon ſo many yeares Exiled with his deare ſoveraigne, and pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient Maſter; yet I shal proceed in the firſt place to that affect, which wee nominate a <hi>Frency</hi> which in truth is more properly the termination of al diſcourſe it
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:45272:33"/>ſelfe being the privation of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, conjunct with a fever, and in this caſe, whither wine may be commonly adhibited, is the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence amongſt the <hi>ancient,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hippoc. lib. de af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tern.</note> ſome commending, others doubting; <hi>Hippocrates</hi> affirmeth, the uſe of wine convenient, in all perturba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the mind, <hi>Tralianus</hi> in the ſame condition, where the ſpirits are Spent, the ventricle cold, and debil, and upon the appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of ſome concoction, in vigi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancie, or defect of reſt, becauſe of its narcotique qualitie, which is moſt ſure, &amp; agreable to humane nature, and for this ſpecial rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, <hi>Epicurus</hi> hath taken it in large proportion, not only in all pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full affects, but alſo in the article of death, in a <hi>palſie</hi> alſo, which af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect obtayneth amongſt the <hi>Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cians</hi> many appellations,<note place="margin">Galen. <hi>2.</hi> Gal. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> Scil: <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raliſia,</hi> and <hi>Gal: paraplexià,</hi> by the
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:45272:33"/>major part of Phiſitians, to be ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended of the ſame ſignifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and that all the tearms ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie privation of ſenſe, and motion, in a ſenſible moving part; Whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>wine</hi> be uſeful in this affect, is much controverted; <hi>Halyabbas,</hi> and <hi>Avicen,</hi> in this caſe appeare <hi>Hydropoſians,</hi> or water drinkers, and render this reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for the non adhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition of <hi>wine,</hi> in this affect, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe ſay they, <hi>Wine</hi> is a proper ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hicle, of humors to the nerues, &amp; by its sharpnes, or pungent qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie, doth enervate, and by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequent foment the diſeaſe; To which I anſwer, that no kind of <hi>wine</hi> moderately taken, and with out any mixture, can, or doth e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nervate <hi>quatenus vinum,</hi> becauſe it nourisheth above any thing, and therefore is the moſt proper cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rective of ſuch sharpe humors, becauſe it breeds, ſo ſweet aliment
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:45272:34"/>
               <hi>ergo</hi> no vehicle of enervation, as they would have it; nor for their water drinking, without the aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of more exact Philoſophy, can I apprehend a greater enemy to the nerves, then cold, nor any congregation, both of heteroge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nealls, homogenealls, or ligation of ſence, equally powerful to the qualitie of cold, but if they intend medicate water, it wil obtain leſſe cenſure, though not received a comparative with <hi>wine,</hi> which uſed with moderation, by its dul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced nature, doth exceed all corro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boratives, either <hi>chymically,</hi> or <hi>ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenically</hi> prepared, and ordained, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially, when the affect is chro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicall, for ſome times the affect proveth acute in the beginning, and then indicateth a thinner nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triment, but pure water according to <hi>Ariſt,</hi> doth not nourish, as hath bin formerly diſputed, in my tract
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:45272:34"/>of waters; In <hi>Spaſmo,</hi> or a convul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive motion when the moving fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cultie is depraved, wil be a quae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion controverted, of the ſame nature, concerning the uſe of this juyce; <hi>Celſus</hi> in this affect, doth prohibit the uſe of <hi>Wine,</hi> with better reaſon then either <hi>Avicen,</hi> or <hi>Halyabbas,</hi> becauſe wine doth dilate, and thus contract the ner<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ves, which ſenſibly appeareth to all artificers,<note place="margin">Hippoc. <hi>5.</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pher. <hi>2.</hi> de morb.</note> educated by ſenſible precepts, to induce convulſions, according to <hi>Hippoc,</hi> and not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the conſent of <hi>Avicen</hi> and <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rapio</hi> in this caſe the adhibition of dilute <hi>wine,</hi> in reconciliation of theſe authors, <hi>Celſus</hi> muſt by my ſelfe be underſtood to ſpeake of this affect, <hi>quatenus</hi> in <hi>principio;</hi> and if my memory in ſo long exile both from my Country, &amp; books (by that ever curſed Parlament of 1641. fayle me not) theſe are his
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:45272:35"/>owne words, <hi>In principio nequaquam convenit vinum, ubi</hi> autem <hi>morbus de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clinare incipit,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hippoc. <hi>4.</hi> de acu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis.</note> 
               <hi>vinum convenit, quia</hi> magis <hi>diſſipat,</hi> &amp; <hi>attenuat,</hi> and after the ſame manner <hi>Hippoc.</hi> muſt be underſtood, where he ordaineth <hi>wine,</hi> for although wine may not be ſo convenient in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of a convulſion, yet in the progreſſe of the diſeaſe, muſt be a proper adjuvant; In <hi>opthalmia,</hi> or inflammation of the eyes <hi>Mercu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rialis</hi> ordaineth <hi>wine</hi> in the declen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, for the unqueſtionable drinke, without any mixture, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it doth then concoct, and determine the diſeaſe,<note place="margin">Galen. <hi>6.</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phor. <hi>31.</hi>
               </note> eſpecially generated of cold matter, &amp; cauſe blood, in which caſe <hi>Galen</hi> affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth <hi>vinum</hi> generoſum, and that he hath effected this cure, by the ſame meanes in a <hi>pleurîſie,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hippoc. <hi>3.</hi> de Morbis.</note> which is a <hi>phlegmon,</hi> of the membrane ſuccinct the Ribbs. <hi>Hippoc.</hi> ordai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:45272:35"/>the uſe of ſweet <hi>wine,</hi> as an in craſſative, and expectorative which are moſt properly indica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from the inflammation it ſelfe yet the ſtricter ſort of Phiſitians are of opinio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, this book, <hi>reputationis cauſa,</hi> was by the <hi>Cnydians</hi> compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, &amp; published, under his name,<note place="margin">Hippoc. l. de acut.</note> the doubt is raiſed, out of his owne booke de <hi>acutis,</hi> where he damneth the Cyndian Phyſitians for their ignorance, and want of regular goverment in the diaeting affected perſons, yet none can ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept againſt the uſe of hot quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, as adverſe to the breaſt; In a <hi>cyncope,</hi> or paſſion of the heart, which although moſt diſeaſes in their courſe, offer offence to this part, yet I could never meet with any, that by a ſpecial excellencie, or proprietie were affects of this noble part, but theſe two <hi>Scil: af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectus ſyncopalis,</hi> and <hi>palpitatio
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:45272:36"/>cordis,</hi> and theſe have their prime localitie in the heart, in the firſt of theſe paſſions, and in all ſuch per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons affected, the conſidiration is, how convenient, the uſe of wine wil appeare,<note place="margin">Gal. l. <hi>1.</hi> ad Glane <hi>14</hi> Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod. <hi>22</hi> Avicen <hi>11.</hi> Cap. <hi>3.</hi> de Sinc.</note> being for aliment, or medicament much doubted, by ſome Phyſitians, becauſe <hi>Galen,</hi> &amp; <hi>Avicen</hi> doe except againſt the uſe of <hi>wine</hi> as obnoxious to ſuch per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, as are afflicted from the head or labour with ingent <hi>feavors;</hi> To which I anſwer though this paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the heart, may be more oppreſſed with ſuch conſent of parts, and complication of affects, yet <hi>extra paroxiſmum,</hi> or upon the leaſt appearance of victory in nature, where refection of ſpent ſpirits is indicated, there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing ſo ſafe, and ſuddayne to ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect it as <hi>wine,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Averr. <hi>7</hi> Collect. <hi>7</hi>
               </note> in this reſpect it is by a compulſive neceſſitie, to be abhibited, and <hi>Averroes</hi> is of my
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:45272:36"/>ſence in this caſe, as alſo the <hi>Sara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceus</hi> amongſt whom it was a cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome or law, not to taſt of wine ordinarily, yet in ſuch neceſſitie they were permitted <hi>wine,</hi> and in this paſſion, as the beſt remedie, ſo is it alſo in <hi>palpitatione Cordis;</hi> or in the unnatural beating of the heart leaſt by the deficiencie of ſpirit, or any other preternatural Conatus, the aegrotant fall into the former paſſion, which is a ſyncope; pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided in this palpitation the wine be old, and pure; Amongſt the various diſeaſes of the <hi>ventricle,</hi> I ſhal only reſt upon the Canine appetite, or the unnatural luſt af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter meat, becauſe it admitteth more doubt, then any of the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedent affects, wine being gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally granted by conſent both Theologicall, and humane, to be moſt proper to excite a depraved appetite,<note place="margin">Hyppoc: <hi>2.</hi> aph. <hi>21</hi>
               </note> according to its proper
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:45272:37"/>acception, for ſome <hi>wine</hi> accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to <hi>Hyppocrates,</hi> doth extin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh hunger, and <hi>Galen:</hi> doth in his interpretation conceive him principally to intend this canine appetite, and the ſpecifique <hi>wine</hi> to be moſt pure, and without mixture; &amp; in my owne opinion, where this affect ſhal proceed from a cold, and depraved humor, vitiating the retentive faculty, the uſe of wine pure is an excellent remedy;<note place="margin">Hippoc: de arte veter.</note> and yet I meet an excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in <hi>Hyppoc:</hi> though <hi>wine</hi> be pure, yet if old (that is ſuperan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuated) and luſty, ſuch as wee call <hi>Vinum vetus generoſum,</hi> by him is not in this caſe permitted,<note place="margin">Galen: <hi>7.</hi> meth.</note> by which it is manifeſt that he tooke notice of the ſpecificall difference in wines, <hi>Galen:</hi> alſo is of the ſame ſence, but they muſt by my com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment be underſtood of exceſſe, which will deject the appetite, &amp;
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:45272:37"/>ſo prove a <hi>bonum preſens,</hi> but if this exceſſe prove vomitorius, and ſo clenſe the ventricle of the morbid cauſe, then 't is a plaine curative; Concerning immoderate thirſt, which is conjunct with al feavors, and of it ſelf an immoderate, or exceſſive appetite of moiſture, whither <hi>wine</hi> of any degree, may encreaſe, or extinguiſh this ſym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptome, is the doubt; becauſe <hi>ſicci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie</hi> by the rule of contrarietie, can not be corrected but with humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditie, therefore wine being gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally by the moſt Phiſitians in France adjudged hot and dry, can not be granted a remedy in this caſe; the reaſons of their opinion, I can conceive to be no other then they render for Phlebotomie, in all affects, and at all times, ages, and ſexes, and the mode of France is their ſole argument, and they would have others accept it a De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrative,
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:45272:38"/>I am ſure in neither opinion, either <hi>Grecians, Arabians,</hi> or learned Modernes will joyne Iſſue with them; <hi>Galen:</hi> will have the ſweeteſt <hi>wine</hi> to be the moſt moyſt of all other <hi>liquids,</hi> and though it doth heat; 't is <hi>calefactio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne temperata,</hi> which is no praeter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naturall, or intemperate caliditie, and both <hi>Galen:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hyppoc: ſalut diae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>30.</hi>
               </note> and <hi>Hippoc:</hi> teſtifie ſmall dilute wine doth quench, or extinguiſh thirſt, much more in a ſmall quantity, then fountaine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>water in a large meaſur, of one time, or by often repetition, for theſe reaſons, becauſe dilute wine is cold &amp; moiſt, ergo moſt proper to correct hot and dry, and extin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh thirſt; there is alſo a more penetrative power in wine, then in water, and as humective, there fore doth ſooner determine thirſt; and my ſelf have many yeares ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved in the higheſt feavors, one
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:45272:38"/>draught of dilute wine, to effect more then many flagons of water, or ſuch like, cold decoctions, nor can any Phyſitian ſatisfie ſuch thirſt with water, and not tumble upon this rock ſcil: extinction, or debilitation of naturall heat, with praeternaturalie in <hi>illeo,</hi> or the twi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting of the bowells, which affect ſometime is a conſequent of the collique, &amp; by which they are of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten ſtrangled, &amp; a diſeaſe, not fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently noted in Medicall books; <hi>Celius Aurel:</hi> ſaith that the <hi>Pythago<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reans</hi> in Sicile,<note place="margin">Cal: an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rel. l. <hi>3.</hi> de acut. paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>s,</note> were accuſtomed to nominate this diſeaſe <hi>Sepimen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum,</hi> as if there were a hedge, ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rating the bowells, others call in <hi>Volentus,</hi> or rowling of the bowells over each other <hi>Scribonius,</hi> &amp; <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellus</hi> doth name it a <hi>Phlegmon,</hi> or inflammation both of ſmall and great guts, others call it <hi>tormen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum acutum &amp; illiacam paſſionem,</hi> and
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:45272:39"/>theſe appellations will be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged; for no sharpe payne (in my opinion) can be inflicted upon a ſenſible body; whither <hi>Wine</hi> in this grand inflammation, may be conducible, will prove a quarrell between <hi>Hippoc:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hop: <hi>3.</hi> de morb:</note> and <hi>Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius,</hi> the one ordayning the drin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of generoſe <hi>wine</hi> in this caſe; the other abſolutely damning it in the whole courſe of cure; by which doth appear a grand miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>underſtanding, in my laſt Author, concerning <hi>Hippoc:</hi> and a rash cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, becauſe <hi>Hippoc:</hi> in that place forementioned, doth conceive this affect to proceed principally from a cold cauſe, and ſuch hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mors are more reaſonably diſſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by generous wine, then any other; and mine owne reaſon of this remedy is grounded upon the non paſſage of excrements in this diſeaſe, and the neceſſity of nutri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:45272:39"/>by which it will appeare, that from this remedy, can pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed no oneration of the body with excrements, becauſe it lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth none, or any that paſſeth thorough any Port, or paſſage, but the bladder; and for aliment, no other ſuccus, ſo ſpeedy and inof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenſive. The antecedent affect being the diſturbance of the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptacles of dry excrements, it wil not look like a diſorderly motion to commit to every conſideration ſuch affects, as doe moleſt the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptacles of moiſt excrements, &amp; principally the obſtruction of the Rhenes, which parts were dedica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by nature to no other uſe elce, but to ſeparat <hi>ſeroſoshumores</hi> fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the blood, &amp; conveigh them through the body, by thoſe ducts, &amp; chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nells according to the univerſall opinion of all Phiſitians, ſince therefore this is their office, and
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:45272:40"/>that this percolation is hindered often by oppilation from ſeverall cauſes, producing various affects, the moſt common cauſe being the <hi>Stone,</hi> and that in the cavity of the Rhenes, though other affects are ſubjected in the ſubſtantiall parts thereof; The Queſtion now is, whither the drinking ſulphureous waters, or wine, doth moſt condu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce to the cure of this affect.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Avicenna</hi> adjudgeth the drinking of <hi>Thermall</hi> waters, either in a ſmal, or great quantity, to procure great difficulty in piſſing, and though the grand compreſſion of ſuch wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters in a large proportion may force a ſtone, into the pot, yet not without exceeding difficulty and agitation of ſettled humors, from which violence, &amp; forced motion proceedeth <hi>excoriations,</hi> ulcers and various diſtempers as dangerous and troubleſome as the former
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:45272:40"/>obſtruction, therefore in this caſe white ſubtile <hi>wine</hi> that is not aſtringent, is better approved then ſuch waters; therfore in the right regiment of dyet, in this diſtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, white wine is to be preferred before incertayne mineral tinctu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res, and if they were certainly known, and perfectly ſeparated, yet cannot the practice be juſtified ſafe, becauſe <hi>Natura non patitur af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictionem,</hi> and many rules admitt exception, ſo doth this except againſt violence to nature; mine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralls therefore, being in their own nature more heterogeneall to ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mals, then any vegetall, muſt (though moſt exactly prepared) offer violence to natur; as for the ſtone in the bladder, I ſhall joyne with <hi>Paracelſus</hi> &amp; his <hi>nil niſi cultrum</hi> &amp; preſcribe no other remedy, but the knife. For other medicines of ſeveral formes and matter, though
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:45272:41"/>
               <hi>Capevactius</hi> drew me over his diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe with many ſcore probats, yet is forced with this parentheſis to conclude. <hi>Sed ingenuè fateor me neſcire quid poteſt lapidem veſicae fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gere, Mercurialis</hi> in a flux of blood from the Rhenes adviſeth, abſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nence from <hi>Wine omnino,</hi> &amp; in the place ordayneth calybrate water, which is a poore corroborative in a grand flux, and expence of ſpirit continually, nor is it incraſſative, or corrective, of acrimonie, te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuity, and ſharpnes of humors, being the principall cauſes of ſuch diſtempers (except eruption, or perforation of the urine) there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore under favour, I shal as boldly and more reaſonably (I ſuppoſe) ordayne the uſe of black, &amp; thick wine, not only to incraſſate, and dulicifie the humor in the firſt cauſes, but as a better ſanative in eruption of the urine, and for the
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:45272:41"/>refreſhment, and refection of ſpirit, more reaſonably to be adhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bited, then any calybeate vvater, though better prepared vvith the juyce of pomegranats and quin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces; In our ſubſequent diſcourſe, vvee cannot avoyd the bladder, as one of the forenamed receptacles of liquid humors, and having be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore determined the only cure of the ſtone generated in this part, by a petrefiring quality conferring thereunto, I shall diluci'dly, with out prolixity, render my ſenſe concerning the ſuppreſſion diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty, ſtillicide, or voiding urine by drops, theſe being proper di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſes of the bladder, though di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſly contracted, from other vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cine parts, cauſally, but ſubjected in the bladder, as <hi>ſubjectum bene diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitum,</hi> to receive ſuch confluen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, the number and differences of ſuch cauſalls vvill offer too much
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:45272:42"/>prolixity for this short underta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, for an <hi>iſcuria</hi> or ſuppreſſion of urine, admitteth of very much diſpute in medicall ſcholes, about the cauſes eſſentiall, and acciden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall, therefore I shall only paſſe to the proper remedies of ſuch affect ſo cauſed.<note place="margin">Hippoc: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>. Aph. <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>4.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Hippoc:</hi> telleth me that all cold qualities are enemies to the bladder from whoſe teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thoſe remedies, which are ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed to that part, muſt be poten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tially hot, and if wee conſider the membranous ſubſtance, and exan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guitie of the part, wee shall ſoon apprehend his reaſon, that all cold is highly offenſive to nervie ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances, nor can there appeare to my intellect any more, then one ſcope of cure in all the forenamed diſeaſes, and that is diereticall, or ſuch meat, or medicine as doth not violently provoke, but gently move urine, elſe one affliction is
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:45272:42"/>added to the other; therefore I shal preſent pure wine as the moſt convenient, dyaretique, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out diſpute, if the cauſe be as cold, as the part. In order of place, the next Lecture muſt be of the diſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of the penis, the word needeth no other interpretation, there are not only ſuch affects, as labefact the bladder, but alſo ſuch as vitiate the action of the penis, I shall therfore relate thoſe affects which hinder the proper action of this part, for although it be dedicated to conveigh urine, out of the bladder, yet moſt properly for the propagation, of the ſpecies, which cannot be effected without ere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, and ejaculation, the firſt may appeare without the other, and then propagation cannot ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed, which is demonſtrated in this affect, which wee call <hi>Priapiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus,</hi> which is an extenſion and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:45272:43"/>of the penis, without de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire of Venerie; Concerning the tractation of this diſeaſe wee can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but take notice of the name, as alſo the nature, the name I could never find in <hi>Hipp:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Galen. <hi>6.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>e loc. af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ect. Cap. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> nor any other ancient writers (except Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len) by whom is rendred the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rivation of the name from <hi>Priapus</hi> who was much noted for the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnitude and extenſion of this vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rile member,<note place="margin">Gal <hi>14.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ethod. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ap. <hi>7.</hi>
               </note> 't is alſo nominated <hi>Satyriaſis,</hi> by <hi>Galen,</hi> and <hi>AEtius,</hi> lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the reader to take notice of the difference amongſt writers concerning theſe tearms, as to prolix (eſpecially) when they may receive better ſatisfaction from <hi>Egineta,</hi> and <hi>Cal. Aurel;</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the nature of this affect, shall be my principall conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion which conſiſteth in exten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, and erection of the member without power of ejaculation,
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:45272:43"/>though it doth proced both from a ſeminal, as well as a flatuent ſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulation, this being the nature of the infirmity, I cannot conceive the moderat uſe of generous <hi>Wine,</hi> for recovery, to be improperly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicated, becauſe it aboliſheth all crudities, and indigeſtions which are cauſes of flatulency, and doth generate a lively blood which doth effect powerfull matter: o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers there are which extract this affect from externall cauſes, both hot and cold, taking the ground of their opinion from brutes, which generally forbeare <hi>coition,</hi> or copulation in the winter and height of Sommer; and becauſe univerſall temper of women, is more cold then of men; therefore their deſires are leſſe in winter, &amp; men more in Summer apt to Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerious action; in both theſe cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,<note place="margin">Ariſt. <hi>4.</hi> Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blem.</note> the uſe of the fore named <hi>Wine</hi>
               <pb n="74" facs="tcp:45272:44"/>is neceſſarily indicated, becauſe the exceſſive heat doth diſſipate the Central ſpirits to the circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference, by which the concoctive facultie is ſo debilitated, as can ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect nothing but ſuch crudities as are cauſes of flatulency, oppila<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and putrefaction, which ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicall and fluent ſpirits vagrant, are retracted, to the center by <hi>Wine</hi> and the parts enabled to execute their offices; in the other caſe when the ſpirits are allmoſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinct with exceſſive cold, the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate uſe of this juyce is the cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dial refreshment. <hi>The paynes</hi> of the joynts which are called <hi>Antriticall,</hi> will beget a great diſpute, or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſie, with vulgar practicers whither or not, <hi>Wine</hi> may be granted, in ſuch doloriferous af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects in the joynts, confiſting of the juncture of bones with ner<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ves, which nervy ſubſtance, is the
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:45272:44"/>ſole capacity of theſe paynes, as being the principall organs of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>act ſence, and that ſence of payne ſo extractive, as ordinarily doth move, both ſpirits and humors, with ſuch violence, as doth in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flame themſelves, &amp; by the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon received opinion, <hi>Wine</hi> can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but more inflame; and ſuch vulgars doe as often and erroni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly nominate theſe paynes of the bones, though the bones are no more ſenſible of payne then the nayles, or hayre in clipping, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to <hi>Ariſt. Galen,</hi> and <hi>Avicen</hi> in many places;<note place="margin">Ariſt. de part ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal. <hi>9.</hi> Gal. l. <hi>16.</hi> d. uſe partium. Hippoc. l. de af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectis.</note> The cauſes inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall of theſe articulate paynes move upon one hinge of <hi>Hippo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crates,</hi> which he calleth humors, and they muſt be congeſted <hi>extra locum,</hi> and in themſelves are more or leſſe vitious; flatulency in this affect will have no share by the conſent of Mercurialis; and for
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:45272:45"/>my own ſence of <hi>Hippocrates</hi> in that place, it cannot expreſſe any other humor, then yellow choller, or atred or a mixture of both, for phlegme by its viſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity and craſſitude, cannot pene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trate ſuch ſenſible ſparts, nor can it effect any pain, <hi>niſi</hi> dolor gravis which cauſe being granted, I shall make very good uſe of <hi>Wine contra omnes gentes,</hi> for where there is any complication of phlegme, by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of its craſſitude and gravitie, it abateth much the punctorious payne of the article, but doth ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect more permanency of payne, becauſe it cannot paſſe through the pores by ſo quick exſudation; whither wine in this condition may be conducible to the cure, &amp; when, is the ſubſequent diſcourſe, and a knowne controverſy in this caſe, therefore I shall rneder the ſence of the moſt exact writers,
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:45272:45"/>and then take boldnes to preſent my own; <hi>Mercurialis</hi> with alothers agre, that in the beginning of this diſtemper from a cholerique cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe, no kind of wine can be granted convenient, yet in the declenſion of the diſeaſe they with <hi>Avicen</hi> doe permitt the uſe of it; how this de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſion is to be apprehended (un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der favour) is ambiguous, for I cannot underſtand this declina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to be ſuch, as doth fully de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine the affect, for then their opinions ſignifie nothing, <hi>quia omnia Sana Sanis,</hi> and no rationall Phyſitian wil forbid the moderate uſe of wine, after a perfect re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery of the diſtemper, let it be of what nature ſoever; therefore they muſt be underſtood of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clenſion in <hi>ſtatu morbi;</hi> yet the proper <hi>wine</hi> that doth correct that hot and bilious humour, and with more celeritie, open the poroſitie,
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:45272:46"/>of the parts affected, cannot (ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept puritanically) be ojbected a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt, neither in the beginning, State, nor declination of the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſe, ariſing from the foreſayd bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lious cauſe; as for the complicate cauſe, I doubt not of the conſent and ſamenes, of fence in approba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the moderate uſe of <hi>Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nish</hi> wine, that is ſubtill and old, but in the thinner acrimonious cauſe, I have adhibited pure whit wine, and in a large quantitie, not only to correct that which was fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xed, but to evacute that which was fluent, both by urine and ſweat, and by its <hi>narcotique</hi> quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, to moderate the intollerable paine of the part, but where viſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity carrieth to the part only a tin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture of choller there I shall pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent <hi>Spanish</hi> wine, and it is the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance of <hi>Rhaſis</hi> in the gout of the feet proceding from ſuch cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe,
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:45272:46"/>
               <hi>Hipp.</hi> alloweth <hi>Vinum</hi> dulce in a bilious predominancy, but that,<note place="margin">Hippoc. l. de af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tern.</note> but that book is taken from an aſcript of the indian Phyſitians, who never were excellent in the diaeteticall part of Phyſique, I shal now con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude all theſe diſputes with a <hi>pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trid feavor,</hi> and then give ſome ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compt of the beſt moderne con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſultations in particular caſes, both hot and cold; The tractation of feavors in their differences, would be of litle conſideration, becauſe <hi>Galen</hi> wil have all acute diſeaſes to be ſimply putrid feavors,<note place="margin">Galen. <hi>3.</hi> Cap. <hi>8.</hi> de differ. reſpir. lib. <hi>1.</hi> de different. ſebr. Cap. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> or conjunct with them, and it is a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived opinion of the ancients, that al feavors (except Epheme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall) are putrid,<note place="margin">Hippoc. l. de vit. Medici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na.</note> and <hi>Hippocrates</hi> will have <hi>neque</hi> Calidum, <hi>neque</hi> fri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gidum per ſe; to be the cauſe of feavors, <hi>ſed aliquid amarum, &amp; acer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bum,</hi> but a quality of ſalt or bitter, or sharp predominancie; &amp; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:45272:47"/>his ſenſe is, that all febrile heat, proceedeth from the predo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minate motion of and alteration of pure humors, to impurity, <hi>Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len, Plato, Athenaeus,</hi> are al of this fence, therefore it doth behoove Phyſitians to perpend not only the univerſal cauſe, and nature of putrefaction, but alſo the reaſon of correction, which is my ſcope at preſent, therefore with the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cients I apprehend putrefaction, to ſignifie a mutation of perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction or puritie, to imperfection and impuritie,<note place="margin">Galen. lib. <hi>10.</hi> Meth. <hi>8.</hi>
               </note> as when wine is changed to vinegar. <hi>Galen</hi> concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth, putrefaction to be a muta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the whole putrefying ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, and effected by external &amp; ambient heat, by which mutation <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> underſtandeth corruptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; by <hi>Galen</hi> I (ſuppoſe underſtood a mutation to corruption,) there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore bodies are leſſe putreable in
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:45272:47"/>winter, then in ſummer, becauſe external ambient heat is then more minute, both in ayre, and water.</p>
            <p>What reaſon wee shall render of cure is the expectation of the reader, who wil as ſuddainly, take notice of my indication, properly extracted or deduced from the nature of putrefaction; which ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to <hi>Galen</hi> is the corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble diſpoſition in humors from a cauſe either internall or external, and accordingly, doe preſent for a remedie <hi>omniquaque,</hi> dilute wine, not ſuch as is mixed with water, but ſuch as in its own nature is more, or hath more of the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queous, then <hi>vinous</hi> qualitie, and yet ſo naturally complexioned, as will appeare a corrective, or alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rative, to praeternaturall ſiccity, and impure humidity; ergo the conſequence muſt be a roduction
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:45272:48"/>to harmony, <hi>quia Sanitas eſt nil niſi harmonia,</hi> as alſo an apt prevention of putredinous diſtempers, which according to the judgement of the ancients, doe proceed from oppilation, nothing being more moderately aperient then ſuch wine, nor more tartarous; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I have made obſervation of ſuch perſons, accuſtomed to the uſe of wine, according to their age, and clime, or without ſuch acception, not to have bin ſubject to putrid feavors, nor can any perſon demonſtrate wine, per ſe, and ſpecifically, ordained ever the mother of ſuch miſchief, though many have ſuffered diſtempers fro exceſſe, which is the vice of the beſt aliment and the worſt, yet ſuch accidents fell not from the nature, or quality of <hi>wine</hi> (though in exceſſe) but from the preſent ſoporiſique quality, vvhich, vvith
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:45272:48"/>out prevention, muſt ſucceed, and vvith cure for the beſt, for ſleep ſtoppeth all evacuation (except ſweat) &amp; vvine naturally moving from the center to the circumfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, and their negligent poſture, in the ambient cloſing the poroſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the body univerſally, by this povver conjunct vvith the endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour of nature, to deliver it ſelfe, of a burthen, doth by its violent motion, in flame ſpirits &amp; conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently this febril diſtemper; pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trefaction in this place and caſe, is excepted, according to vulgar ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce; nor can the ſubtilty of logique, being an incommodum upon this vinoſe remoedy,<note place="margin">Galen. <hi>2.</hi> de acut.</note> 
               <hi>Galen</hi> dot maintain the rationality of it as a remedy in putrid feavors, &amp; therefore com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended the Italian mode in adhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biting in al feavors, <hi>Vinum Sabinum,</hi> and confeſſeth in the ſame firſt book Cap. 40. that himſelfe was
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:45272:49"/>accuſtomed to cure putrid fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vors, after the ſame manner, and if any wil take notice of <hi>Hîppocrates,</hi> not only in his book de acut, but in others, they ſhal find my bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes in this practice grounded upon himſelfe, whoſe ſoul I could deſire above all terreſtriality, not that I deſir o<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly to act or cloath my ſelf with a part, or habit of a Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitian, as players doe the Perſons of Kings and noble Perſons, no ſooner diſnobled &amp; diſrobed, but rogued; I am not ignorant of the diverſity of Medicall ſects, not doe condemne any (but moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters) but from this digreſſion I shal tranſire to thoſe ſtrict Phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians which doe condemne the uſe of wine, not only in this caſe but in al feavorish diſtempers, but becauſe they render no reaſon, I cannot judge their ſect for Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thodiſts argue with reaſon, and
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:45272:49"/>Empericks a particulari (though not the beſt Logick) yet if it be poſſible to bring them into the ſect of rationaliſts I shall aſſiſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with this exception in <hi>Galen:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Galen. Meth. <hi>11.</hi> &amp; <hi>12.</hi> ad Glauc.</note> which is againſt the uſe of any wine, in theſe foure ſubſequent caſes, firſt when the feavor is ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hement, ſecondly, when there is a conjunct payne from the head, the third is, <hi>in delirio,</hi> which is a deception of reaſon, and laſtly, when the <hi>origo</hi> of this putrid fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vor is from, or doth, follow an inflammation.</p>
            <p>Under favour, the differences of wine obſerved, wil reſpond all theſe objections, as ſmall dilute wine in all inflammations, and more liberally, or in a larger doſſe preſcribed doth abate, if not abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lish all vehemency, and by its ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porifick quality doth coligate the ſenſes, and reconcile ſleep, which
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:45272:50"/>is the diminution of all vehement ſymptomes, delyration, and shar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſt paynes of the head, which imperite Phyſitians, more dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerouſly force by opiate prepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and I shall conclude with the ſame Authority I began this diſcouſe,<note place="margin">Galen. <hi>11.</hi> Meth. <hi>9.</hi> Galen. l. <hi>1.</hi> de An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tid. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> and render the affirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Galen, that this kind of wine, is moſt convenient in putrid cauſes, to provoke urine, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coct crudities, or ſemiconcocted humors, and wil not admitt the mixture of water, more then it receiveth from the plant; and this is the determination of the que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, concerning the application or uſe of wine in feavors; Now I shal proceed to various affects, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout which the moſt learned Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dernes have conſulted; whither the uſe of wine in them might be conducible to cure, becauſe ſome are hot, the others cold diſtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers,
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:45272:50"/>and begin with a Iew that laboured with Melancholy, his temper hot &amp; dry, from a vitious predominancie over the blood, his body leane, colour black, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſpoſed to ſleep, prompt to all action, prone to anger, of an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent witt and diſcourſe, but at this preſent Mute, and hath bin ſo theſe ſix dayes, his temper thus agreed upon, with his diſtemper, by a counſell of Doctors; they now fix upon two ſcopes of cure, the one moiſtning, the other ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning obſtructions, and in both, <hi>wine</hi> is concluded a proper reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die; There was alſo another great conſult about a Cannon of Rome, labouring with a feavor, whither wine might be preſcribed; about this point was much controverſy, but concluded, and adhibited the remedie; Nor doe I read of any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Medicament in all this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſultation;
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:45272:51"/>ſutation; In the next place, I pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent a young Gentlewoman la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouring with an Epilepſie, or fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling ſicknes, her temper hot, and moiſt, and ſo concluded in coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell, becauſe they found her body fat, and fleashy, in this caſe they determined the uſe of wine moſt convenient, for the attenuation of humors, and corroboration of all noble parts; The ſame was agreed upon for a young Spanyard in a burning feavor, in a great diſtilla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, pro Epiſcopo Lucenſi; in various diſtempers pro Aloyſio Foſcareno; in vertigine or diſſines of the head, pro cive Lucenſi; a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt al effects of the Rhenes and bladder, pro Magnifico Contare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no, with many others which were too prolix to produce, enough being argued to inſtruct the uſe of wine, in all tempers, to be moſt natural aliment, and in all diſtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers,
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:45272:51"/>as proper medicament, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded by the moſt learned, an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient, and Moderne in Medicine; Thus farre have I urged the uſe of pure <hi>Wine,</hi> not that I am ignorant of the excellent advantage in me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicall wines, the ordinance of which is left to the judgement, &amp; direction of the preſent agent, my ſelfe paſſing now to every age and ſex, to shew the proper uſe of wine for aliment in each, and the time when; my former diſcourſe hath tended more to medicament then aliment, which is to be the ſubject of our following diſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe, though not ſo immixed but ſome vigencie may intervene.</p>
            <p>Humane bodies, are not only obnoxious, daily to affects of ayre, dyet, exercize, paſſions of the mind &amp;c: but alſo from our im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>planted, and internall heat, which by degrees, more, or leſſe, doth dry
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:45272:52"/>up, and demolish our origenall humidity, which in ſome ſence ariſeth out of it ſelf, and by this perpetual motion, is ſo conſumed, as doth effect many mutations, which are conſcribed with certayn periods, and converſions of ages; for every animal newly procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, or pullulant <hi>ex ſemine, &amp; ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guine</hi> and compounded of its prime humidity, is moſt humide, in whom all parts organicall, as bones, cartilages, &amp; flesh, are ſoft, tender, and flexible, which by pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion in age, doth ſtiffen, dry, wither and conſume, in the like mode, are the viciſſitudes, and mutations of temperaments, and diſtempers, with their conjuncts; therefore age is but a motion meaſured out by time, in which the conſtitution of the body, by it ſelf is perſpicuouſly changed; Six not able differences of ages,
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:45272:52"/>with their temperaments, are to be obſerved; the firſt the child age, which extendeth from the birth to the 14. or 15. year, &amp; in temper, hot, and moiſt, and is more hot, then ripe, and juvenall age, by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of fixed heat, for by how much neerer it is, to its originall, by ſo much the more doth it participate of innate heat, contrarily, by how much it doth receed from its firſt principles, by ſo much is the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate heat exhauſted; And this age, one of the ancients divideth into foure orders, infancy, dentity, and media between theſe, and ripe age, and laſtly puberty, which pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenteth it ſelf aptly to be diſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, as the ſecond age in the order of nature; This age of puberty begins at the fiveteenth year, and is extended to the eighteenth, and is leſſe moiſt, but more hot; The third age is adoleſcency,
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:45272:53"/>which beginneth at the nine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teenth year, and is extended to twenty five, and of a moderate temper; The fourth age is juvenil, or flourishing young age, which beginneth at the 25. year and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendeth to thirty five, and is more hot and dry in temper then the precedent age; The fift age is virill and the <hi>media</hi> between young and old age yet doth it not ſo partici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pate of either, as to affect, or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temperate it, as it beginneth at thirty five, ſo it extendeth to fourty nine; The laſt is old age, which by the expence of naturall heat in temper is cold and dry, the moiſture being excrementitious, by reaſon of languishing and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cayed heat; This laſt age, as the firſt doth admit of diviſion into theſe three parts, the firſt is fresh old age, beginning at fifty, and extendeth to ſixtie, and all this
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:45272:53"/>time is ſerviceable to the country in execution of Offices, which may comply with their former e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducation, the ſecond age is a me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dia, or middle old age, beginning at ſixty, and extending to ſeventy, and in this age moſt men are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerviceable for their country, or ſelves; the laſt decrepid age, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning at ſeventy, and is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly extended to eighty; and with this age our terreſtical being &amp; life is concluded; not but ſome extraordinarie puritie in the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipals of ſome individualls, which may cauſe a larger extention of life; Theſe are the common dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferences of humane age, the firſt ingreſſe hot and moiſt, the laſt egreſſe, cold and dry, the middle temperate and proved ſo to be by every ſence; And thus is the life of man,<note place="margin">Iob.</note> which ſpringeth up like a flower and with a short duration
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:45272:54"/>in one State, circled out a puncto, ad punctum, and shall render it probable by art, to extend mans life, and preſerve it from the ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of ſome diſtempers, conveig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hed in the naturall principles of their mixture, commonly recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved for diſtempers hereditarie; &amp; defence to be cauſed by the right uſe, and application of this juyce, from which familiarity with uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſall nature, life is extended beyond all expectation; which is ſuch a defenſitive in weak tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers, as doth enable to reſiſt faci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble aſſaults, conveighed in <hi>materia ſpermatica.</hi> The beſt oportunity of effecting ſuch undertaking, is <hi>ab incunabolis,</hi> or from the breaſt of the mother and ſo proceed from temper to temper, as they admit of mutation, in their ſeverall ages, otherwiſe, the univerſall temper may be ſo injured, as ſpoyled, by
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:45272:54"/>antecedent irregularity, both of dyet, and medicine, as will cauſe great difficulty in future under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takings; for though much advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age of time be gayned, yet the perfection of cure, or full ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of the creature, will not be obtayned. I could render an Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pyricall argument from my own affect which was then an Atrophia totius corporis, or conſumption of the whole body, and left by the moſt perite Phyſitians as incura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble; my valitudinary temper then, being untill the age of thirty years, affrighted at the ſight of one glaſs of wine, being a ſtrict obſerver of ſuch advice, as muſt be accompted more learned, then my own young ſtudies could produce; but when I was left to my free choyce, of any thing my reaſon could preſent, or appetite require, upon thoſe grounds of Philoſophy which I
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:45272:55"/>had meditated, I did caſt my An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chor at the root of this plant, and by the conſtant uſe of the juyce recovered in the ſpace of twelve moneths perfection of cure, and have in ſuch ſtate of health conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued twenty and two years after, and voyd of a conſumptive diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition to this day, &amp; have in many others ſince obſerved ſuch <hi>levamen</hi> as in a latitude, may be eſteemed a cure; and the right uſe and appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of this juyce cannot be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyed, in purity to exceed all ſper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matique humors, ſucked either from women, or breaſts, according to ancient &amp; more moderne pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive; This is a Nectar, and Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broſia for Princes and as pleaſant contemplation for Phiſitians, learnedly to undertake the practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce of it; for as this life may be ſaid to be the <hi>unum neceſſarium,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe upon this point eternite
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:45272:55"/>doth, or may depend, and that the lives of Kings are more conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, then other Individualls, as being the ſouls of their King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and people, it cannot but encourage the ſtudy of all Phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians, for the particular, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon ſafety, and preſervation of this Iewel, to endeavor a right underſtanding of the uſe, and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication of the blood of the gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pe; and the moſt learned, in their higheſt contemplations, shall find this ſubject worthy of their indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry, as their exceding expreſſions, above this my velle, wil hereafter manifeſt; if I should relate my many difficult, and diſputable cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res, of my own effecting, in a mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude of ſeveralls, it might not onely ſeeme oſtentative, but alſo an act of injuſtice, and non inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grity to others to publish perſons with their imperfections, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:45272:56"/>to my cure, &amp; ſecrecy; nor is teſtimony in this caſe of ſuch abſolut neceſſity, where the point is rationally cleared, &amp; conſented unto, by the moſt learned fathers, and Shoolemen in the faculty of Medicine; upon which ground I shall deſire credit, and eſteeme in the firſt place, and ſo returne from my digreſſion, to my proper ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, and try whither I can make it ſuitable to all ages; The infant age is the firſt, &amp; moſt difficult to reconcile, becauſe Galen ſaith, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the colection of Frabeſarius, <hi>vinum infantibus fit noci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vum,</hi> becauſe their temper is hot and moiſt, but ſuerely he was bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter acquainted with the ſence, and ſoul of Galen, to conceive him ſpeaking of the ſpecifical differen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce of ſuch wine, as is indicated for nutriment in this age, for then he muſt challenge him of ſuch miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>underſtanding
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:45272:56"/>of Phyloſophy, as not to comprehend, mixed bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies to be ſupported and nouri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed, by their ſimile, and force him ignorant <hi>of ijs nutrimus, quibus conſtamus,</hi> or that ſuch mixed qualities properly applyed, are unapt, or inſufficient in their own nature, to aſſimilate with their identitie, or ſamenes, as is the mixture of wine, to our materiall principles of nature; but Galen cannot be underſtood of the qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, but ſuper exceeding quanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, which as too much oyle doth extinguish the Lampe, or diſtur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be it by moving ſome other hete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogeneal which by the true ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port of wine nature had been a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble inſenſibly to have diſpoſed o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe, for had the nature of wine in it ſelf appeared to Hippo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crates abnoxions he would never have ordained the dieting of
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:45272:57"/>children in the ſtone either of the rhenes or bladder ad hereditary to conſiſt of white wine rather then milk nor was he ignorant that he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reditary diſeaſes were Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated to the children any other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe then in their ſpermatick principles, nor that wine in it ſelfe and its own nature could be diſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greable in the ſupport of thoſe principles, or to foment &amp; main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain their conſtitutions, with out any morbificall motion or altera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, my ſelf hath alſo much uſed it in affects of the ſame natur and in many other with exceeding approbation from ſuceſſe, nor can I conceive wine hurtfull to any temper of it ſelf without the miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>application and indiſcretion of the agent not knowing the ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficall differences and mode or uſe, by theſe expreſſions (I preſume) the underſtanding reader to have
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:45272:57"/>received ſatisfaction for the firſt age &amp; that it is abſolved from the former prohibition and at liberty freely to make uſe of wine, now I am to preſent a health to the next order which wee called pubertie, this temper being more hot, and leſſe moiſt then the former yet by ſuch wine as doth contemper the heat, and adde to hte moiſture, that wine wil and muſt prove pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly uſefull to this age, the time when &amp; quanteties how much as well as the quanteties ought to be directed by the phyſitian, who muſt neceſſarely obey his indica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and proper ſcopes, Adoleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency being of a middle temper &amp; predominancy neither hot nor cold nor moiſt or dry, will mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rately and with obſervation of tyme, clyme, and quanteties, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitt of white, clarret and rhenish wines with out any fear, Iuven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:45272:58"/>being of a temper more hot and dry muſt with the former a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects apply it ſelf to the forena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med wines, and if they ſenſibly appear not ſufficiently moiſtning, 't is ſooner effected by the addi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of fountaine water. Verile age from thirty five to four<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty nine broatcheth a veſſel of more rich clarret and paſſeth out with a taiſt of the ſmal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſt ſack which ſenectus maketh,<note place="margin">Bolonia wine.</note> more ſtrong by more rith ſack, muſcadins and aligants, and conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nueth their uſe to the utter extent and period of life, having thus ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed it to every age and cleared my propoſition, the next conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration will concerne the ſex, male and faemale, which though ſome have more out of curioſity then utillity differenced their tempers, moſt of their litigation beeing <hi>de lana Caprina</hi> or the various tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peraments
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:45272:58"/>of ſexes affirming wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men muſt of neceſſity be ſelled in the left ſide, and therefore more debill and cold then men, which if it be granted for the ſatisfaction of ſuch fancy, yet my obſervation is with out any difference ſo a liene, &amp; my opinion in the poynt, is alſo that temperaments are not conflate out of heat more obtuſe, or vehement (though it may ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie ſome thing ingeſtation) but depend on the perfuſion and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of the four elements, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore having formerly more di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinctly diſcourſed of tempera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, I have alſo included ſexes, and now paſſe to the mode of uſeing this ſubject, all my former labour hath been a Phyloſophical extraction and ſeparation of wine, in its principles and medically taught the familiar uſe, both for aliment and medicament, not
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:45272:59"/>doubting its general acceptation, and were it not agreeable in the ſame ſenſe to ſuch uſe I shal inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niouſly acknowledge my non un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding of Ariſtotle his ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentm ſimile and diſſimile for al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though all aliment of het coldeſt quality muſt receive a forme of heat before it can be produced in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a nutritive act, yet is there no ſuch forme or ſubſtance ſo tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cible and naturally diſpoſed to ſanguification and nutrition as the blood of the grape, and an au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gmentation of radicall moiſture or inuates heat may be granted, their can be nothing in humane conception more apt to effect it, for tis oleagenous and a juſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition fomenteth the flame, which aquoſitie doth extinguish, ſo as it is the true nectar, by the uſe where of the principles of life are augmented, naturall humors
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:45272:59"/>multiplied, ſpirits created and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freshed, ſtrength reſtored, care expelled, and juvency or youth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe concerved, to conclude, it is the all to a naturall body, for a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liment in generall is and by com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon conſent granted to be liquid ayrie, and ſold which qualities are the complement of this juyce, I have alſo proved it a convenient medicament in the moſt difficult and diſputable affects of the body and if I should recomend the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe of pure wine, or an opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive doſſe once every month the Arabian Phyſitian will juſtify my Ordinance, as hath appeared by their own practice and ſelf cuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me affirming it to recreat the ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal faculties, reconcile ſleep pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voks urine and ſweat, diſſolve ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfluities and a certaine cure in a quartain fever with many other diſtempers, circumſtances condu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cible
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:45272:60"/>obſerved, which circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces I have given notice of in the precedent diſcourſe, and reſolved to entertaine this time with ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, only take notice of cuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me to be in a latitude or ſome conſideration ſubſtantial, becauſe it over ruleth or comprehendeth as a ſecond nature both time and clyme, and there are ſome as neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary accommodations to the right uſe of this aliment as condiments are to ntritive ſubſtances of an other condition, as principally the direction of, and conſult with the Phyſitian, for let the temper or diſtemper be of any nature (ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept gangranous, or wounds vice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rat, by his right and proper appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation they shal ſenſibly perceive a refreshment and prolongation of life, without which nothing is pleaſant to univerſall nature, for what is aliment with out an appe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tite
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:45272:60"/>or land, when the owner can not trample it, or any other de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light to an incapacity; The chimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal ſect urge the pleaſantneſſe of their extract as a grand beauty in their medicine, but heere I preſent a ſafety and pleaſantneſſe tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cending all minerall opperations, and effected by an undoubted re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giment of fire, and to be preferred Prince of all other vegitalls; ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe in this juce may be more ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily repaired, and the diſtemper more ſpeedely and inoffencively reduced to harmonie, the princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal difficulty wilbe in obteining pure wine with out ſophiſtication, for which cauſe, I can cordially kommend, as much as deſire the Scotish ſeverity eſtablished, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the English nation, and that the Sophiſticatiors of wine, may ſuffer punishment above any ordinary theef, as not onely pic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:45272:61"/>the purſe of all nations, but with a ſecret venene mixture paynfully afflicting them, &amp; often irrecoverably, no vetrickle being ſo proper to conveigh any malig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity or venemous quality to the univerſall ſpirits of any creature then wine, if I shall diſpute fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, ſome may take me up for prolixity, and others ſtop me for a <hi>non viſitavit,</hi> well knowing that <hi>Galen:</hi> with his commentary upon the Aphoriſimes tranſlated, urgeth that wine <hi>as venus</hi> doth debilitate innervate, and Frambeſarius will according to the Frensh mode ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alt a meſſe of pottage Frensh, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond a chine of English beefe and therefore addeth theſe inſignifica<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t <hi>(Scil) vinum venuſque nocent eodem modo</hi> &amp; if hee or any other under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand or undertake <hi>Galen:</hi> in that literal ſenſe, they muſt confute him beyond <hi>Iohannes Argenterius</hi>
               <pb n="109" facs="tcp:45272:61"/>with whom I left <hi>Ranchnius</hi> his Countriman at foyles, and leave it to thoſe of leaſure or ſtanders by, to divulge the victory, but if in that litteral ſenſe apprehended the objection I confeſſe is inſtar ommium whether it be taken for the uſe, or exceſſe of wine, and in the firſt ſenſe it wil affront greater artiſts, and in the ſecond oppoſite to the <hi>Arabians</hi> which hath told the <hi>Graecians</hi> and other oppoſits that their Countty is their diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace, and thoſe oſtentators a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace to their Country, Avicen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na, Rhaſis, and Averrhoes adviſe it <hi>uſque ad Ebrietatem,</hi> the challeng is high and whither they have meaſured their weapons (I know not) but if <hi>Galen</hi> be not under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood to ſpeake of Ebriety, then neither the uſe of wine or women can either debilitate or be abno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctious, for both in their orderly
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:45272:62"/>mode are of much utility and concernment, the one to preſerve the individuall, the other the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pagation of the ſpecies, the firſt hath been largely diſputed, the laſt which concerneth propaga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion not to be effected, but by an act venerial, which Avicenna in a melancholick predominance con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demneth, but in his 20 and 3 chap:<note place="margin">Avicen: <hi>1.</hi> Tract. <hi>3.</hi> Cap <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>de juvamentis Coitus</hi> (ſaith) that the uſe of venerie doth moſt help the melancholiſt, which opinion was accepted before from <hi>Paulus Aegineta</hi> in his firſt book <hi>de rebus veneriis,</hi> by which it will appeare in Avicen: contradiction of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, and to redeeme him out of ſuch incommoduments; let us perpend ſome paſſages of <hi>Galen:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Galen. <hi>6.</hi> Epid. Coment <hi>5.</hi> Text <hi>25.</hi>
               </note> where he affirmeth mixtion to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraine diſeaſes in fieri or in their motion, and <hi>Galen:</hi> will not ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit of any other interpretation of
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:45272:62"/>
               <hi>Hipp:</hi> but that mixtion and Coi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion are of the ſame ſignification and amongſt other affects doth digitate melancholie, affirming moderate Coition or uſe of vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie to be a ſpecifick remedy, (eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially proceeding from vapors of combuſt humors) and with out queſtion upon this conſideration, the moderate uſe of Venus is a conſiderable adjuvant, but if wee underſtand, or accept thoſe fit ſubjects of ſuch remedy, as are af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected by pungent vapors from a predominancy of naturall melan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cholie, this flatulencie beeing more cold (though provocative) in this ſenſe the uſe of venerie doth prove verry adverſe, and in this ſenſe I underſtand Avicen: and the exception in <hi>Galen:</hi> prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipally to reflect upon, both quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity and quality unſeaſonably ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied, both in reſpect of tyme and
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:45272:63"/>temper, as when the wine is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecificall to the temper or quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity exceeding a naturall capacity and upon an empty body <hi>ubi vacuis committere venis nil niſi lene decet,</hi> and then immoderately to exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe the act of venery, after ſuch a mode both wine and women are innervations and great conſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives of ſixt and fluent ſpirits, and where <hi>Plato</hi> and <hi>Ambroſius</hi> have an exception I apprehend it only of the nimium, which is intoxica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or ebriety in a voluptuous courſe which doth obnubulate reaſon and ſenſe rendring the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon inferior to a meere animal &amp; a vice reproved by all rationales not only as it is pernitious to the body, inflaming the blood, debili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tating the nerves and afflicting the head, but as a privation of rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon which is the forme of man and by which he preceadeth all other
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:45272:63"/>terreſtriall creatures; but I am not of opinion, that thoſe Arabian Princes, did ever uſe wine in ſuch a voluptious manner themſelves, or adviſed it to others but medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally, as will appear by their monthly preſcription, upon pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per indication, preferring wine before any other medicine, becau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe of its operate power, ſo fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liarly reſpondent to nature. This objection beeing cvleared I ſhall move to the laſt extracted from ſacred ſcripture. There are a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valent ſect in England and other places where they have gayned permiſſion, that ſtiffely defend with inconſiderable logick, that the fatality of mans life &amp; actions and ſuch conſiderations, are but as the judgement of men which is foolishneſſe with God, becauſe (ſay they) no man can be in life or fortune preſerved, prolonged, aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted,
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:45272:64"/>or reſtored to either, becauſe diſeaſes with all their Concomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants are, or muſt be inflicted by an inexpugnable neceſſity deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined of the Almighty and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mutably fixed, and the cloſeſt councel of God, have ſuch cloſe clipt conſiderations of their op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ponents, as if with out ſpectacles they could not ſee their lowſy Crownes, or not diſcerne them ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicalous to intellectual perſons, and pernitious to all Kingdomes and juſt people therof, upon this pretended ground of Religion they murther, ſteale, betray inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cents, perjure themſelves, rebell a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt God, their King and coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, ſuppoſing no eye can ſee the Phariſaicall pathes they walke in, nor that they keep in memory the old cheate of the grand Phariſie, who made it a damnable ſinne for the publican to dreſſe meat
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:45272:64"/>upon the Saboth, and the ſame Hyppocrite, upon the ſame day made a great feaſt and invitation to our (Lord and Saviour) that he might obteyne advantage of his diſcourſe, and in a Traterous un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertaking (ſaith hee) 't is lavvfull to breake a Comman dement, for ſuch a breatch of command and trechery at this or that time vvas, and is by the inevitable ordinance of the Almighty, and if God ſhall command othervviſe they are Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viathans and vvill acknovvledge no ſupreame above <hi>naturam natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratam</hi> and vvithout controle doe vvhat they pleaſe as doth daily ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear (amongſt the reſt of their cheates) their blaſphemous faſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings and prayers, vvhich is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but a plaine mocking of omnipotency, or a requeſt to deny his ovvn commands, for if he vvil not give a contrary command to
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:45272:65"/>murder, theft, adultery, perjury, or diſobedience and disloyalty, their actions bid defiance, and tell, in ſpight of his vvill or povver they vvill doe it, as gyants of force to unthrovvn the Gods, and then they uſe Demetrius his faemenine vveapons to ſlay their uxorious husbands, and then the people muſt be cheated vvith the preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce of Religion and the name of God, vvhich themſelves muſt take in to their declarations (though they hate Reformation) and perſwade the people upon this hyppocriticall ground, that it is but a ſuperfluous curioſity of ſome fine woven bbravnes, to avoid contagion, or to ſeeke remedies correcting or curring affects (yet their blaſphemous prayers and faſting shall never effect) or to arme themſelves againſt their ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myes and for the ſame reaſon that
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:45272:65"/>God foreſeeth death of every mode in time shorter or longer and his irriſiſtable order in ſuch motion to bee in a voidable, and yet the ſame omnipotent, bath de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared to all humane nature, that the perdition of every perſon is of him ſelfe, otherwiſe he can be no delinquent in his juſtice, if by a ſupreame power inevitably obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged to ſuch actions or paſſions: how pernitious and impious this hereticall doctrine appeareth to reaſon and common ſenſe is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood, (except ſuch intellect as apprehend nothing either of rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon or ſenſe, but that which is bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in to their skulls with apole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>axe) and whoſoever alloweth this error muſt of neceſſity diſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low of that forme of prayer for our daily bread, ordred by our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour to be an inſcience in him and a peece of Rebellion againſt
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:45272:66"/>his aeternal Father in ſuch a reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of his eſtablished will, as alſo all the divine prayers for the prolongation of life, and preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation from danger, ordred by his Apoſtles and their ſucceſſors, as alſo the dispenſation of the guift of healing to the Phiſitian. If all diſeaſes and diſſolutions of every knide be ſo imuiovably predeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nated as cannot admit of any re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy, or to what end or purpoſe did the almighty omniſcient, crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te &amp; honour the Phiſitian, to ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the reaſon will ſilence Mr. <hi>Speaker</hi> and both houſes of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, therefore under favour of more learned interpretors of lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning in theſe poynts, I shall doe my own indeavour rationally to expurge this pernitious and intol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerable error concerning divine providence, and to this purpoſe, ſome thing concerning his caele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtial
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:45272:66"/>adminiſtration of univerſalls, are to be taken in to conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and repeated, by which the dignity and eximious utillity of medicine may be more clearly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrated. That therefore the viciſſitudes and actions of things and humane nature, are not by chance, but by the ordination of the Almighty, ought to be a prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple embraced by all Chriſtian people, and that God is the omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potent and aeternall fabricator of the whole univerſe out of nothing as is affirmed by divine teſtimony, this aedifice beeing ſo powerfully erected is alſo by the ſame efficacy conſerved, who hath alſo appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to every created thing, both a beginning &amp; end, or termination of ſubſiſting and moving, and doth take notice not only of prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall but alſo of ſubſequent cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of things, as if that God did
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:45272:67"/>governe, moderate, diſpoſe and order them, according to his free will, and yet all this government is void of fatall violence, and moſt commonly commeth to effect, mediately, and from deputed cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, which vulgarly are nominated ſecond cauſes, which the divine Majeſty doth imploy as the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments of his will, ſo long as he doth ſo governe all things vvhich he hath created, as alſo him ſelfe may ſuffer them to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe their proper motions, for the vvill of man by divine ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is the originall of humane actions, freely electing vvhat ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth beſt for it ſelf (eſpecially in externalls) and the nature of mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is the cauſe of this or an other thing in vvhich it is <hi>per ſe,</hi> accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to <hi>Ariſtotel</hi> as in the Sun per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuall rotation, and in grave and beavy bodyes their inclination to
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:45272:67"/>their Center, and the cauſes ſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpond the effects, as if the effects be neceſſary the cauſes are alſo neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary, &amp; if contingents, the cauſes are contingents, nor doth the prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience which is certaine &amp; not to be deceaved, abolish the contin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gency of naturall events, but the future effect is diſpoſed as it were by a divine providence neceſſarily or contingently, nor doth it nul the freedome of the agent, nor is the creator obliged to the neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, but moderateth al things frely according to his free wil and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, as did evidently appear when he cauſed the ſun to ſtand ſtil, or move retrograde the ſpace of one compleat day, and cauſed the red Sea to divide and ſtand like firme wales, without either flux or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flux or any motion that wee read of, until the Iſraelites had paſſed over them, as alſo in the caſe of
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:45272:68"/>Daniel, and the three children in the fiery furnace, and Duffus Mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>columbus King of Scots who was moſt barberouſly murthered Anno Dom: 961. after which ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to their own hiſtory there was no apperance either of the Sun or moone for the ſpace of ſix months, and though divine omnipotency can diſpoſ of cauſes and life with every kind of death at his own free pleaſure, yet it wil not urge any perſon to accept, that terme of life for a fatall determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, but for a divine ordination of ſervient cauſes and their natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral power of ſuſtaining or corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting life, for ſince life (according to the Phyloſopher) is in its ſelfe but a duration of heat conjunct with moyſture, which duration of vitall heat and extinction of the ſame are naturall effects, depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding upon naturall cauſes, which
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:45272:68"/>doubtleſſe, becauſe of the various diſpoſition of internall heat and moyſture, complicated which ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall cauſes, not only the quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, but alſo the quantety of life it ſelfe may be varied, for it doth ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyn the internal conditio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of live<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly principles, ſo long as the heat &amp; moiſture are ſo united in animals, that one is not deſtroyed or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turbed by the other ſo long they ſubſiſt, but either of them ſepera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted each from the other perish, and in whom ſoever innate heat is more vegetious &amp; ſtrong, and ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dical moyſture more pure in ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance and exceeding in quantety, recipient of a juſt temper which is <hi>temperamentum ad juſtitia,</hi> in ſuch life is more durable and perma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent, and if any inquiery shalbe made into cauſes of long life, in the fore-fathers to the years of nine hundred and more they wil
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:45272:69"/>graunt the internall purety of principles to be the cauſes of ſuch extenſion of life, and ſucceſſively abreviated by time, in which mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſuffiety decay, as not poſſeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ve of the prime purety, therefore in theſe ages the counteſſe of Des<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mond, and Thomas Parre are ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinarie exemples, for ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narie old age is threeſcore &amp; ten, if one climicterick more it muſt be effected by the extraordinary power &amp; purity of radical princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples: for radicall heat is the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall agent of generation, in the liquid ſubſtance of ſeed and blood in the firſt conception, ſoone after renders it more dry, and delinea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth the rudiments of every mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, and by a farther ſiccity, doth publish the exact ſpecies, and after its production into the world, it doth bring it to perfection, and by the continuat efficiency of this
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:45272:69"/>heat the parts are ſo exiccated a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove a moderate proportion, as doth render them leſſe (if not una<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble) to performe their proper fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, by which there doth fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low a neceſſity of decay, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinction of naturall heat, and this is a naturall death (according to-Galen) which by reaſon of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tream ſiccity, and non nutrition, this naturall progreſſe to old age without any ſenſe of payne vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sheth in a regular motion, from generation to corruption and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cay, and is unnaturall and vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent when by any other internall, or external cauſe is extinct, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore this naturall motion to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treame old age which by a skil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full order may be prolonged a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt internal cauſes (except a depraved wil) which deſtroyeth many individuals which no reaſon can deny in capeable of extream
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:45272:70"/>duration one ſtory I remember of a diſcontented gallant which drowned himſelf, and being much lamented by the ſpectators for youthful comlineſſe, amongſt them was one of this erronious ſect which was pleaſed to read a lectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re to them of the inevitable dicree of the Almighty and not by him to be avoided nor by them lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, Ayong man (of the contrarie education) gave hir a great blow over the face, which made hir challeng him of baſe Cowardice, and as great incivillity to the fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menine ſect, who returned hir in anſwer, that it was the in evitable will of God it should be ſo, and a truth according to hir own do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, which cauſed hir to ſtagger in hir opinion leaving this digreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, I muſt returne to my Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophicall diſcourſe of heat and moiſture, ſo united as waiſteth no
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:45272:70"/>otherwiſe then by their own natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral motion with out diſorderly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juries of phyſick or dyet, therfore doe proceed upon the ſimile of Hippocrates, by which he compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth the life of man to a lamp or candel, preſerved in a temperate place, free from any tempeſt in ſuch a place the candel wil extend to the laſt ſparke of fire or moiſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re, otherwiſe by any tempeſtious or violent aſſault, of any kind it is extinguished before it be half li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ghted, or if its halbe moved gently in a large (though not tempeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous aire) yet that motion being more immoderate will cauſe it to blaze out ſome howers before o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe it would in a temperate poſture, the like injuries and prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternaturall aſſaults to humane bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, are plagues, wounds and al o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther diſtempers, ſome peracutes ſuddainly extinguishing life, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:45272:71"/>abreviating, &amp; the leaſt and mildeſt diſtemper obteineth ſuch immoderate motion of ſpirits as in ſuch a digre doth expend a por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of natural heat and moiſture, as doth according to that digree abreviate life, the firſt violence compelling nature ſuddainly to yeeld up all power of motion, the latter effecting the ſame cunctan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do, I cannot but confeſſe, as mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter admitteth generation, ſo is ther a compulſive neceſſitie of ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering corruption nor can the heart be made moiſter being ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treamely excicated by its motion to old age, yet no ſober ſpirit, can conceive it a point of wiſedome or religion in a careleſs, negligent, or deſperat way, to render up their being in this life, before an irriſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtable neceſſitie for this is like beaſts to be led, or fooles to lead ourſelves to ſlaughter, Thus have
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:45272:71"/>I done my in deavour to clear this laſt objection &amp; to discharge the fatality of mans life of all future quaeſtion, nor the extention of it by care and counſel to extreame old age, and by no ſuch naturall meanes as wine, and if I should proceed further to every cercum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance conducible to the practicall part, it would be a work of long tyme which I cannot ſpare, and of exact judgement, wherein I could be content to receive directions, from guides more quick ſighted and learned then my ſelfe. That which I have now written is ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to my own reaſon and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire, to give more ſatisfaction to the world concerning the uſe of this vinoſe ſubject, which hath been doubtful and in al ages quae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtionable, both in reſpect of the life of man, whether or not it may be extended, or whether it be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenſible
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:45272:72"/>as alſo in reſpect of wine, whether their proper nature be ſo extending, as in all the former di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe hath been my laboure to demonſtrate, by arguments both a priore <hi>&amp; a poſteriore,</hi> and by ſuch argumentatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to in counter thoſe fantaſtick sculs, that either can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not, or will not conceive the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>decinal art, to be eſtabliſhed upon any other ground (except conje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture) and that the beſt conjecture is the beſt Phyſitian, not under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding that pathognomik ſym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tomes demonſtrate the affect, as plainly as any other shadow doth either man or beaſt, none that hath eyes will take the shaddow of man for a horſe, nor of an oxe, for a rhinoſoros, or a lyon, for a bear, to ſuch as theſe I doe not di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect this my Phyloſophy, nor can I conceive where there are ſuch infinities of faces, their should
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:45272:72"/>not alſo be a varietie of opinions, therefore I cannot hope to ſatisfy every fancy nor doe I intend to be underſtood of the vulgar, but leav my juſtification to the naturall ſonnes of art, and to ſuch are theſe my indeavours preſented, an obla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion after the manner of thoſe di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vote children, which where accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomed once every year to offer a ſacrifice to Iupiter, but at the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſtomed time being by an inex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected inundatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> prevented, both of their altar and Sacrefice, inſtead of a beaſt, they offred a lemon which Iupiter accepted in that ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitious condition, ſo alſo thoſe that have read my precedent Tract of waters, cannot conceive my head free from washing, nor my braynes from ſuch inundation, as conſequently may not dilute my wine and render it more weak and impure, yet if my devotion may
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:45272:73"/>be acceptable to Iupiter, let it be bleſt to the world, and where as (like the dogg of Hercules) I have be ſmeered my lips with the Crimſon juce of the grape, other Herculian braines, may vent it in more pure, and plentifull in ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance and meaſure, by which eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſenſe shalbe refreshed, every capacity filled, and every intellect really delighted.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>Pag. 63. line. 8. preternaturalie for preternatural. p. idem l. 20. volentus for volvulus. p. 79. l. 4. indian Phyſitians for Cnydian Phyſitians. p. 83. l. 2. cure for care p: 94. l: 15. facible for forcible. p: 96. l: 16. Breaſts, for Beaſts, p: 98. l: 23. then for elce, p: 104. l: 7. her for the, p: 108. l: 4. vetrickle for vehickle.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:45272:73"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
